<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned and a very profitable exposition made vpon the CXI. psalme</title>
            <author>Travers, Robert, fl. 1561-1572.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855452</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855452</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13878)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1119:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned and a very profitable exposition made vpon the CXI. psalme</title>
                  <author>Travers, Robert, fl. 1561-1572.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Vautroullier dwelling in the Blackfriers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Robert Travers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20947:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LEARNED AND A VERY PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FITABLE EXPOSITION made vpon the CXI. Pſalme.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Vautroullier dwelling in the Blackfriers. 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20947:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20947:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, THE MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>TE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, FELOVVES, SCHOLLERS, and other Students of the Colledge of the holy &amp; vndiuided Trinity in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, Grace, mercy, and peace, from God our Father, and from our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>GAINST griefe conceiued in the death of a vvorthy friende, often times ſuccour is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ghte in a Tombe or other monument, thereby to deliuer the deades vertue &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable life, from the vnkinde forgetfulneſſe of vnthankfull men. Therefore vvith the familie of the author of this booke, and vvith me alſo vvhich in good vvill to him in his life, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for his death come next vnto them, it falleth out very well, that the ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce which our poore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate denieth vs, the learned diligence of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed friends, by making at vnarares his owne tombe in his life time, hath ſupplied vnto vs. Now if by dedication of it vnto you, it be (as it were) ſette vp in your Colledge, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall be (I hope) a thankefull worke: conſidering that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you looke to the kinde of a tombe in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or to this in particuler, the worke bringeth
<pb facs="tcp:20947:3"/> you commendations from them both. For wheras other tombes are often times the generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of full c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſers, without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany had with any great vertue or ſinguler learning, this is the birth of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſanctifying by the true feare and knowledge of God. And where others come out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoppe, this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of the ſchole, and that of Chriſt: Thoſe may bring vs ſome meſſage of death, but theſe bring alſo the good tidings of life, and that in death: vvith a number ſuch preheminences, for which as this kinde of monument ought of right to haue the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the other, ſo ought it to haue gladder eyes to looke rather vpon it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the other. And as for the ſpeciall matter which commendeth this tombe, it may be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the workeman of it moſt plentifully. He was firſt by a ſcholership, and after by a felowship planted in your Colledge: Therefore it will rellie the better that it is frute of your owne planting: The worke was both made and vttered in your Colledge, and for it alone: if you shoulde not therefore prepare your ſelues at the warning of others, be yet in a readines at the voyce of your owne, and proper trumpet. It coſt him the loſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his felowship, I might haue ſayde of his life: which by quietnes in his Colledge, should likely haue bene prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged. So that herein it is prouided euen for them, to whom dayntie things are not dedicate vnleſſe they be deare bought. If you
<pb facs="tcp:20947:3"/> looke alſo that it ſhoulde be farre fetched, the principall and as it were the marble thereof was taken from the higheſt heauen, the grauing from the vtmoſt parts of the earth, whither by an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable hunger of reading, he had (ſitting in his ſtudy) trauailed. For, beginning at Rome (I meane the olde and eloquent, not this barbarous Rome) and from thence taking his iorne, into Greece, he landed in Canaan, where he had gotten not the bare &amp; empty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke of the three, the Latine, Greeke, and Hebrue tongues, but with them the good marchandiſe of arts &amp; ſciences contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them. For although in the loue which he bare to a ſimple and plaine handling of the word of God he ſuppreſſed the ſhewe of them, yet, at the faces which are continually in the Sunne can not but be tanned and ſlayned therewith, ſo his ſpeach could not but cary ſome colour of the learning and knowledge wherein he was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conuerſant.</p>
            <p>And as for the chaunge of his life, if a good death doe waſh away the filth of the former life, his death (which was ſuch as my ſoule wiſheth, and hopeth for the like) muſt needes ſet a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> both vppon the reſt of his life that was holily led, and vppon this worke eſpecially, which thorough conſcience of a great dutie diſcharged therein, cauſed him to goe e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ragiouſly to meete with death, and (as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were) to take it by
<pb facs="tcp:20947:4"/> the hande or euer it had taken him.</p>
            <p>Bring hither therefore your eyes: firſt, indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to iudge of the ſinceritie of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrete, that you may diſcerne his ſpirite zelous with iudgement and earneſt in waighty matters: bring thirdly your learned eyes, that as in a peece of tapeſtrie, you may ſee with the varietie of colours, the diuerſitie alſo of the knottes and flowers not onely to looke on, but to take them out and make the like. So ſhall your profite be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and your pleaſure profitable, ſo ſhall you of his loſſe get gayne, &amp; of his payne get pleaſure: finally ſo ſhall that which was to him the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Achor, be vnto you the gate of hope. And I beſeech that holy and bleſſed Trinitie whiche is the patron of your Colledge, that he would ſo fill you with al knowledge, eſpecially of himſelfe, that after you haue brought many to this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſocietie, your ſelues may enter into that holy felowſhip whervnto (in Chriſt) you were choſen before the beginning of the world. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By him which in the reuerende good will he beareth to you, hath taken an obligation of himſelfe, dayly to pray for you.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:20947:4"/>
            <head>THE VERSES OF M. Portus vpon thautor.</head>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I. X. K.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:20947:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20947:5"/>
            <head>A PRAYER.</head>
            <p>THY worde ô Lorde is holy and pure as thy maieſtie: and I of an vncleane hart and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ppes vnworthy either to ſpeake of it, or to profeſſe thy name: yet becauſe of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull rotation I beſeeche thee ſo to ſanctifie me that I may ſpeake of thy word reuerently, and thy children beare fruitfully, not to death and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion, but to life &amp; ſaluation through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="exposition">
            <head>
               <hi>PSAL. CXI.</hi> Praiſe ye the Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>will praiſe the Lorde with all my hart, &amp;c.</hi> I haue choſen to interprete and ſpeake of this CXI. Pſal. for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie and perfitnes of the ſame for although it be but litle &amp; ſhort yet the holy Prophet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth in it the ſumme of many Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. And as when he gaue his minde to the preparing of thoſe thinges which ſhoulde ſerue to the building of the materiall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he diſpoſed in his mind vnto what vſe this and that iewell or waight of gold and ſiluer and a number of other things ſhould be applied: So I doubt not but in theſe Pſalmes which this noble and worthy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20947:6"/> left for the ornaments of the Church of God which is his ſpirituall temple, he had great conſideration whereunto eche Pſalme ſhould ſerue. So the wiſe and godly king appointed ſome to declare the vſe of the Sabbath: others, to remember the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of their deliuerance: ſome to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the prouidence of God in all thinges: and ſo many other Pſalmes he wrote which he conſecrated as tables to the honour of God and prayſe of his mercie for his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance out of his daungers, and as glaſſes for the children of God to ſee their eſtate in. This Pſalme comprehendeth not one or two pointes, but is left vs as a moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and precious diamond, wherein we might ſee almoſt all thinges. For firſt, he celebrateth the goodnes of God which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the whole world: then particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly the benefits beſtowed on his Church: Laſtly, the dutie of the children of God for theſe benefits, with an exhortacion to the feare of God: ſo that this Pſalme is to vs, as many Pſalmes. And for this cauſe it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that he hath laboured to penne and write it artificially. for it is made according to the Hebrewe letters euery halfe verſe, as they are in order beginning with a letter vnto the two laſt verſes, where he putteth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20947:6"/> three in a verſe. Which art and diligence which the ſpirit of God in him hath vſed exhorteth vs to giue diligent heede &amp; care to marke and vnderſtand this Pſalme. For if it become all fleſh to ſtand and giue care when God ſpeaketh, ſurely it becommeth vs to giue an excellent attentiuenes to the Lorde when he vſeth a ſingular maner of writing or ſpeaking, and to adde to our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed diligence, an artificial diligence, where the Lorde ſpeaketh by art, and, as it were, to ſet our cares, where he ſetteth his words. This for vs that are hearers. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are here to learne when God ſhall call vs to the miniſterie of his worde in his Church, that we ought not to come negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, to ſpeake of the workes and mercies of God: leſt by our fooliſhnes and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence the doctrine of God come into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. But to ſtirre vp our mindes and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and all the powers of our witts how we may in moſt excellent, and frutefull kind of preaching ſpeake and vtter it. Therefore it behoueth vs now in the daies of our youth while the Lord of his mercy giueth vs time &amp; oportunitie, that we omit not thoſe good healpes which are fit for our furtherance &amp; profit in theſe ſtudies, neither idly &amp; negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to let the daies &amp; months &amp; yeares
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20947:7"/> paſſe ouer vs without conſideration of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> profiting from time to time: leſt we become but ſlubberers &amp; vnfit inſtruments for the Lords glory and praiſe by our owne naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſlothfulnes and idlenes.</p>
            <q>Praiſe the Lord.</q>
            <p>This is the inſcription or title of this Pſalme: where before he beginneth this ſong he calleth other into the fellowſhip of the ſame exerciſe with him. Wherein we ſe what a notable zeale the Prophet of God had, to the ſetting forthe of the Lordes glorye, who is not content him ſelfe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prayſe God alone, but ſtirreth vppe other alſo thereunto. Doe we thinke that ſuch examples are left in the Scriptures that we ſhoulde ouerlooke them, and not thinke that they are written for our exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Nay doubt we not, but the Lorde hath ſet ſuch lights before vs, that we ſhould take light of them, that we may alſo giue light to others, that by our wordes and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, we ſhoulde alſo ſtirre vppe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame others to the prayſe of God with vs. For if we haue not that affection of calling others, ſurely we deceiue our ſelues if we thinke we loue the Lorde. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not in this Prophet onely we ſee ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20947:7"/> excellent and ſo many exhortations to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to prayſe the Lorde with him, but alſo in many places of the Prophets, and namely in the ſeconde of Eſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 2.3.</note> where he propheſying of the kingdome of Chriſt, bringeth in the people ſtirring one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſaying: <hi>Come and let vs goe vppe to the Mountayne of the Lorde, to the houſe of the God of Iacob, and he shall teache vs his vvaye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and we will walke in his pathes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29</note> So thApoſtle to the Hebrewes ſheweth that it becommeth the children of God to ſtirre vppe one an other to the feare of God, wherevnto he applyeth that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, Comfort one an other, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the weake knees (which is ſpoken of in the Prophet Eſaye) to all the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Eſay</hi> 35.3.</note> So that we may not reſt in our ſelues, if we be in companye, and heare and ſee the Lordes name abuſed, or our brethren and companions abuſe them ſelues in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ſorte, but that in a Chriſtian and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner we ought to admoniſhe them, if not openly, yet at the leaſte ſecretely: and not to be glad onely if we ſee their deformitie, conſidering that it is well with vs in compariſon, but (if we haue the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God) we are bounde to ſeeke their amendement alſo. But what doe I ſpeake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20947:8"/> of admoniſhing others? Ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yther we are mockers, and vnpacient of all admonition, or els we are not fit to ſpeake to others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelues ſo farre behinde. Therefore we ſee heere what we ought to labour to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne vnto, euen to be filled with zeale and godlineſſe, with knowledge and wiſdome, that as the ſea is full of waters, ſo we mayn be full and plentifull in all goodnes, ſo that we may water others with our fulnes. And thus much the title of the Pſalme teacheth vs, for although it was then (when the Pſalme was made) ſpoken to the ſingers, yet now it is ſpoken to vs and all that ſince that time haue bene before vs, or ſhall come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will praiſe the Lorde with my whole harte.</hi> Here followeth nowe that noble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent proteſtation and profeſſion of the praiſe of God which Dauid doth promiſe for the manifold mercies of God. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (as I haue partly ſhewed) the thing which he ſpeaketh of are in deede wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and excellent, and worthy to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet Dauid had no more cauſe to praiſe God for them, then any of vs. For he reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth no priuate benefite to him ſelfe, but euen thoſe which he hath common either with all the world, or els with all the houſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20947:8"/> of Iſrael. It is therefore no leſſe required of vs to whom theſe benefits doe equally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, or vnto whom the Lord hath ſhewed much more exceeding mercye then vpon Dauid and the houſe of Iſraell, that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the ſame vowe and pay it to the Lord. For Dauid deſired to ſee the dayes that we ſee, yet God otherwiſe diſpenſed according to his wiſedome that we ſhoulde ſee them, who yet do not eſteeme them. But if Dauid had liued in theſe times wherein the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Ieſus Chriſt is ſo manifeſt, he woulde no doubt haue ſo farre paſſed that zeale and knowledge that he had then, as we woulde haue bene worſe if we had bene in thoſe darker dayes. Therefore let vs knowe that we all ought to make this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the prayſe of God euen as the benefites of God require of vs, and be no leſſe earneſt to ſing this thankes giuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, than Dauid was: and ſeeing the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites be common, to ioyne with him prayſing God for them. Further we may learne here, what lyeth vppon it if we take vppon vs to call other to the prayſe of God, it is that we our ſelues firſt giue example euen as Dauid, who as he called others, ſo he leadeth firſt and ſheweth the way to them. For if we call others and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20947:9"/> are deafe our ſelues, if we bid other goe, and we ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtill, if we pipe and ſinge to our neighbours, and we be not our ſelues therewith delighted, what doe woe but mocke God and condemne our ſelues. Therefore in the 12.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 12.4.</note> of Eſaye, the faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doe not onely exhorte other, but they beginne the ſonge of prayſe and thankes giuing them ſelues: <hi>I will prayſe the Lorde with my whole harte, &amp;c.</hi> Here the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet teachethe vs a notable doctrine, if we aſcribe not to nature as the prophane Philoſophers, or to ſtarres as vayne men, or to fortune, as the blinde and couetous, or to any other thinge then to the Lorde alone, this excellent order which we ſee in all the worlde, or that redemption and theſe benefites which were beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Iſraell at his departinge out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, but that in bothe we acknowledge onely the wiſedome and mercye of our God, whoſe hande and power brought all theſe thinges to paſſe. Yea let other prayſe their Idolls which they fayne vnto them ſelues with the diſhonour of God, we will O Lorde acknowledge thee, and make mention onely of thy wiſedome and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindnes and truth that hath wrought this goodly order in all the worlde, ſuche
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20947:9"/> mercies and benefites for thy Churche, and ſuche iudgementes againſte the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and them that knowe not thy name. <hi>I will prayſe the Lorde with my whole harte.</hi> Here the Prophet declareth what kinde of thankes giuing and ſonge this ſhall be that he purpoſeth to ſinge vnto the Lorde, not an outwarde and hipocriticall prayſe, not in wordes onely to come neare vnto him, not onely in tongue and mouthe: but an hartie, an earneſt, a true ſonge, a ſonge and Pſalme wherein all the partes and powers of his minde and vnderſtandinge ſhall bee ioyned together in as muche as a man is able. For he meaneth not that thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſonge of prayſe ſhall aunſwer to the exactnes of the Lawe, wherein we are commaunded with all our harte and ſoule to ſerue the Lorde: But the whole harte in this place is oppoſed to a diſſembling and hipocriticall harte, and as he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in an other place, to a harte, and a harte that is a double harte.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> So that here is no holde for anye to take, that man is able to fulfill the Lawe, if we admitte the Holye Ghoſte Interpreter of him ſelfe. But alas, what ſhould I diſpute that man is not able to fulfill that commaundement of the full loue of God which is required, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20947:10"/> is he that dare diſpute for it? I aske no other witneſſe agaynſt himſelfe then his owne conſcience, if he vouchſafe to looke into it. Shall he not there ſee a ſea of wicked thoughtes? a world of vayne deuiſes? a hell of blaſphemies, and foule imaginations? ſhall he not ſee a ſlaue and ſeruaunt of the body, or rather an infinite number euen ſo many bonde men to ſinne, and miniſters to Satan, as he hath partes and members? O the depth, length, and breadth of that wickedneſſe that remayneth and dwelleth in vs! Well the Prophet teacheth vs that knowe our ſelues, that we come not before the Lorde, before whoſe eyes all our hartes are open and manifeſt with a face only and ſhew of godlines, but that together with our tongue, our ſpirite and ſoule be ioyned, and ſo to come to ſing or pray vnto the Lorde. For if we come before the Lorde eyther hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically or negligently, let vs be aſſured that he whoſe honor we ſtaine by our bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and impudencie, will require it of vs to the vttermoſt. It followeth: <hi>In the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and aſſembly of the iuſt,</hi> that is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly and in the face of the Church. For that inwarde and darke godlineſſe that yet men loue ſo muche, that they will prayſe God in their chambers, in their ſtudies, in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20947:10"/> their hartes, that can not ſuffice. Naye, that is no godlineſſe whiche in tyme and place will not openly ſhewe it ſelfe to the prayſe and glory of God. But yet this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and declaration of our ſeruice, that is required of vs, is not ſo muche for the Lordes cauſe, as for our owne certayntie touching our election, and for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of the children of God to the lyke by our example. And if we conſider who this is, and what a man he was that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this, we will eaſilye graunte that I woulde proue. For who was more diligent, earneſt, and often in priuate prayers then Dauid?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.62. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.6.</note> Howe many nightes are witneſſes of his godlyneſſe? in the wilderneſſe, in the mountaynes, and caues of the earth, in his priuie chamber, and in his bedde, howe was he accuſtomed to powre out his ſpirite before the Lorde? Yet we ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this godly and great Prophet exempteth not him ſelfe from publike and common aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, where the children of God were according to the appoyntmente of God gathered to prayſe him, and confeſſe vnto him their ſinnes, and to heare his worde, with other exerciſes for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of hys fayth and godlyneſſe. But what do I ſaye that he did not exempt him
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20947:11"/> ſelfe, whiche thought it the greateſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite vnder heauen to haue a parte and portion in the Churche and communion of Sainctes. Therefore in baniſhment he ſo be wayleth and lamenteth his ſtate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it were by tyrannie excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from that Paradiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 42. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 84.</note> &amp; from that earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heauen, I meane the temple, when were manyfeſt ſignes of the preſence of God. Not that Dauid knewe not but that he moued, and liued, and had his beeing in God, or that the Lorde would not heare his prayers out of the temple, but for the ſame cauſes that euery one of vs ought to be ſo affected to the common places of prayer and hearing the worde, and recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Sacramentes, was this earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in Dauids heart, becauſe there the Lorde had appoynted to be worſhipped, there the ſacrifices to be offred, there the miniſterie of the Prieſtes, there was the fellowſhip of Gods children, there was a Sacrament of the preſence of God, which all more fully, and clearely, and liuely now in euery faythfull congregation gathered according to the worde of God, do appeare to vs then they did in the temple. And yet who accompteth it as the leaſt parte of his croſſe, when he is ſicke or otherwiſe hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20947:11"/> from the ſeruice of God? who conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the happineſſe of their feete that treade in the temple of God? Who wiſheth for his appearance before the Lorde, as the Hart brayeth for the riuers of water, in the congregation? O the wonderfull contempt of the benefites of God, and the ſinguler patience of the Lorde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.3.</note> Moyſes when the people were kepte with Pharaos hande as with a chayne in Egypt, asketh their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce of the king that they might ſerue the Lorde in the wilderneſſe at the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, leaſt the Lorde ſhould ſlea them. And who is he that this daye feareth the hande of the Lorde, if he omitte the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God? I ſay not holden from it by Pharaoh, but tyed with his owne linkes and chaynes which he hath made vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe eyther buſines or ydlenes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But a day wil come when theſe deriders and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of his worde, and the felowſhip of his children, ſhall account it moſt extreme my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie to be ſecluded from them, whom yet heere they contemned. This doctrine is as playne as iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by fayth, or no merits of works, and yet how few authors &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers hath it? But herein appeareth our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that it is in imagination, not in fayth: or opinion, not in iudgement in the braynd,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20947:12"/> not in the heart, in worde not in deede and effect. It followeth, <hi>In the aſſembly of the iuſt.</hi> This is a title whiche Dauid giueth to the Church of God, therby declaring who they are that haue in deede a place in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For although all come both good and badde, both the ſwearer and he that feareth God, both the adulterer and he that made a couenaunt with his eyes, both the vayne and idle perſon, &amp; they that walke in their vocation diligently: yet Dauid did ſee in the worde of God who were right witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the prayſe of God, and therefore as with a rodde he ſtandeth and ſeuereth the wicked from this company.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.1.</note> So in the xv. Pſalme he asketh of God ſeeing all go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who they be that ſhall dwell and abide for euer in his tabernacle? that haue their names as it were written in heauen, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto that companie? and he aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe, that ſuche as are pure and cleane in their workes, he that is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioner, no vſerer, he that feareth God and loueth and maketh muche of them that feare the Lorde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.6.</note> And in the xxiiij. Pſalme, This is that generation of Iacob of them that ſeeke thy face. The reſt are baſtardes, and not the true generation of Iacob. And in the 50. Pſalme the Lorde
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20947:12"/> doth as it were muſter his true children from amongſt all Iſraell, and ſeuereth the wicked, and forbiddeth them to ſacrifice or to do any thing whereby they profeſſed that they ſerued God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16.17.</note> ſeeing they hated to be refourmed, and were fellowes and companions of the wicked. All which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces teache vs how we ought to labour day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by prayer and thoſe meanes that God hath lefte to profite vs, that we maye be counted before God of the number of his true children, he meaneth not that thoſe onely whiche are without ſinne are of the Churche of God, but as it is taken in the Scripture in other places, for ſuche as to their power ſerue God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1.</note> So Iob is called a iuſte man, one that feared God: Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth and Zachary are called iuſt, and Noah a iuſte man: whiche all yet, had their great and many ſinnes: but thoſe he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth heere iuſte who propounded to them ſelues the feare of God to lyue after it: who walked before God in the wayes of righteouſneſſe and holyneſſe, althoughe they ſometime fell: ſo that vnleſſe we haue this before our eyes to lyue according to the worde of God, to come to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or congregation to profite, to putte off
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20947:13"/> dayly ſome peece of our olde man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to bee enriched and decked with Ieſus Chriſte in Wiſedome, Iuſtice, Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sanctification more and more, by our comming to the Churche we pollute the congregation and infect the verye place, and make it a witneſſe againſt vs in the day of iudgemente, and we deſpiſe the holy company of Angelles, who are together preſent with the children of God witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of all their behauiour, and we moche and prouoke the Lorde agaynſt vs. It were better neuer to ſee the Church, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſette foote within the doores, then thus proudly &amp; preſumptuouſly to breake into the temple of God with ſo great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to his name. For what do we make of God, or how do we accompt of him other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then of an Idoll, who neyther ſeeth, heareth, nor knoweth vs, when thus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently we dare take place among the Sainctes of God? Therefore lette euery one that is wicked and purpoſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in his wickedneſſe, heare what I ſaye vnto him in the meſſage of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Theſe gates are the gates of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 118.19</note> as ſayth the Prophet, the righteouſſe ſhall enter into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: this houſe is the houſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20947:13"/> of mine honor, the contemners and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of God haue no inche of roome therein: This companie is the Church of Gods Sainctes and children, there are no dogges or ſwine in this number. Knowe therefore that the verie ſteppes of the Church dore are holie grounde and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be prophaned: knowe that there ſtandeth at the dore the Angell of the Lorde with a ſword in his hand to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy entraunce into this earthly para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, who will ſurely ſmite thee at the laſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24.</note> for all this diſpite againſt the Lord.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 4.24.</note> As for vs that by Gods grace are not giltie of this contempt, let vs ſtill feare God and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe him in ſpirit and truth: let vs be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, ſincere, earneſt, true and faithfull in our duties to God, who will in the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted ſet vs with his Angells for euer to praiſe him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 20.36. <hi>Apo.</hi> 21.27.</note> and will caſt out the polluted and vncleane out of his Church. He will put their names out of the booke of life where they ſeeme to haue bene wrytten,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.33</note> he will caſt out with Iſmaell all mockers and geue them their portion with the goates. This great God &amp; righteous iudge ſaue vs &amp; keepe vs from the temptations of Sathan that we may euer ſticke vnto him in truth &amp; faith. Amen.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20947:14"/>Great are the workes of God ſought out of all that delight therein.</q>
            <p>This is the firſt verſe of the Pſalme of praiſe which Dauid ſingeth to the Lorde. For the former verſe which I haue ſpoken of is but a preface, and a preparing vnto the Pſalme, whereby he ſtirreth vp him ſelfe &amp; other to ſinge, and heare this ſonge. In the beginning therefore of the Pſalme let vs examine and ſearch the whole purpoſe and parts of it, that thend being vnderſtood we may ſee what cauſes, reaſons &amp; arguments are the grounds therof: which be the parts &amp; the ſtrings vpon which he playeth &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth this ſong that if they be common to vs with him, if they be now as mouing as euer they were, we ioyne our ſelues alſo vnto this fellowſhip with him. Firſt therefore he beginneth at the generall and common workes which are in the whole worlde to praiſe God. After theſe two verſes he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth the remembraunce of their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance with thoſe benefits which togither the Lorde ſhewed them, as the ſpoyle of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, the poſſeſſion of the land of Canaan &amp; the benefits of the knowledge of God by his worde, and in theſe pointes conſiſteth this Pſalme. We ſee therefore as I haue ſhewed already that here is no mention of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20947:14"/> any ſpeciall and particuler benefits beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely vppon the Prophet, but that the cauſes pertaine as wel to the whole church of God as to him: whereuppon it followeth that we vnderſtanding this ſonge and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the partes and vaynes of it, we giue our ſelues to no leſſe hartye and earneſt praiſe of God then Dauid hath ſhewed vs example, but that we caſt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eyes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he doth here on euery ſide to obtaine ſome furtheraunce and helpe to ſtirre vs vppe to praiſe the Lorde, let vs then followe the Prophet, as it were ſteppe by ſteppe and ſchole by ſchole, that we may attaine to the like zeale. <hi>Great are the workes, &amp;c.</hi> Here we ſee the firſt ſchole, the firſt maiſters &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors that Dauid had eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the works of God in the whole worlde. Whereby we ſee what ſchole the ſpirit of God trained him vp in, to learne to knowe the Lorde: a ſchole in deede moſt fit to learne the knowledge of God in, if we haue the eyes that Dauid had, and the diligence which from tyme to time the children of God haue beſtowed therein.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19.</note> Therefore it is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtle in the firſt to the Romaines ſayth that which was to be knowen of God that is his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power and Godhead may be knowen by them. For which cauſe he condemneth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20947:15"/> all the wiſe men of the world euen by theſe witneſſes of the glory of God: who though they knew, yet learned not by them to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God as became them, that is in ſpirites But they chaunged the glory of the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and holy God into the ſimilitude of mortall and vncleane beaſtes. Therefore in the firſt Epiſtle to the Corinth. the Apoſtle calleth it wiſedome,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.</note> which God ſet before the worlde when they were without the word and had onely his workes for bookes to read vpon.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17.</note> Therefore laſt of all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth theſe workes of God the rayne and ſeaſonable weather, and ioy of harte, witneſſes of God. We ſee then that that is in deede a ſchoole of wiſedome by the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Scriptures which alſo may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto vs by the effectes of that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and high knowledge which the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers attained euen by them onely. How many of them knewe the prouidence of God? Howe many the immortalitie of the ſoule? the creation of the world, and many other truthes, without the written worde of God? But as th Apoſtle ſayth they attained not to that poynt to worſhippe him aright by theſe things, but they mingled their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes and imaginations together with the truth and their fooliſh harts were darkened<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20947:15"/> that attained not to any profitable know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, further then to make their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation iuſt. But they might haue learned by them the feare and worſhip of God as Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my alſo witneſſeth accuſing the Iewes that euen by the bleſſinges of God they did not learne to feare him who ſo mercifully bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.24.</note> They might well haue learned,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28.</note> ſeeing that we moue and liue and haue our being in God, as certaine of their owne Poets taught them, that Gods power is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite &amp; euerlaſting, that there is one God aboue all things to whom onely honor and worſhippe is due. They that require further to ſee what the Heathen haue learned e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by reaſon I referre them to Iuſtine Martyr <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> where he ſetteth forth largely all that they vnderſtoode by the workes of God. If then the workes of God ſo clearely and manifeſtly haue ſhewed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men onely wiſe and cunning in thinges not pertayninge vnto ſaluation, ſo muche of the knowledge of God, it is a ſhame that we hauinge not onely the workes of thoſe men but alſo our owne experience and the worde of God which teacheth vs further of theſe workes that men of them ſelues vſe to ſeeke, if we become not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie excellentlie and perfectlie learned in
<pb facs="tcp:20947:16"/> thoſe things which the workes of the Lord do teach vs. For we may not thinke that the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were made to gape on, or the earth for to tread vpon, the creatures of God for vs, and we for our ſelues, but we muſt euen, out of all them learne much wiſedom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the knowledge of God, and moſt out of our ſelues. But we haue not that mind to profit that other of the children of God haue ſhewed, and are le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Why are we not all Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that be in Camb. that haue ſuch helpes &amp; meanes left and lent vnto vs of God for our furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce in the knowledge of the things that God hath made? Nay we are as the moſt rude and ignoraunt men and yet ſeeke not for better. If we looke to the heauens, it is a ſealed booke vnto vs, we know nothing of thoſe quarters, we can not heare that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſound and noyce and ſame of God that they ſound to his praiſe. If we looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the earth, vpon the fruts, herbs, &amp; trees, we can not read, we knowe no more then is good for the pot &amp; for our bellies, &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowledge we neither folow nor deſire. I am perſwaded that if that care had bene in men that might and ought to haue bene, neuer a one of vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were firſt bache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers had bene ſo rude and ignorant in theſe
<pb facs="tcp:20947:16"/> moſt noble arts (which many yet know not almoſt by name) as we are nowe euen after ſome yeares that we haue taken the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them vpon vs, we may take heede by the ignorance &amp; negligence of the daies that are paſt, &amp; if we haue not ſuch amongſt vs as can teach them, let vs by rewards and liberall ſtipends prouoke ſome to the ſtudy of them who may be after lightes to other therein. Sure the leaſt pece of learning co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in vnderſtanding quiddities, and I thinke meanes might be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to haue euery ſcholler in this houſe within foure yeares if men had humble mindes that they woulde harken to other (although then inferiours) not onely well learned in the three noble tongues, but alſo in the ſeuen liberall artes &amp; ſciences. This is peraduenture vnſauery to ſome, and ſeemeth to haue ſmall edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but to him that iudgeth a right, he ſhall finde that in Colledges and in Trinity Colledge it ſhould ſeeme hye time for men to lay their handes to it, if we looke either for godlines or learning to floriſhe in it. For howe ſhall we ſee into the workes of God without eyes? howe ſhall we heare without eares? and howe ſhall we vnderſtand what they meane if they ſtill lye hidden from vs? They are all great, excellent, &amp; notable, but
<pb facs="tcp:20947:17"/> as Dauid ſayth <hi>ſought out</hi> and ſearched and inquired into. And if we ſtand to conſider them from Behemoth of whom we read in Iob to the Oiſtrich:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 40.10. 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4.33</note> from the Egle to the flie, from the Cedar of Libanus to the Iſope that groweth vpon the hill, from the ſtarres of heauen to the duſt of the earth, &amp; from the Angells of God to the wormes that creepe vpon the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Theſe are the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our knowledge in the workes of God. Theſe are our borders &amp; limites wherein to ſtay, &amp; yet we thinke we are greatly learned in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, if we knowe almoſt one of them, or a few quiddities of <hi>materia prima</hi> and ſuch like thinges. Oh that we propounded vnto vs at the laſt true &amp; good knowledge, ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d profit &amp; abſolute learning, that man would with a cotage &amp; life ſeeke to labour to his power to attaine vnto it. But Dauid here noteth our fault when he ſaith, <hi>they are ſought out of them that delight therin.</hi> For wherein is our delight but in vanities, but in play, but in pride, but in idlenes, but in pleaſures, but in eating and drinking and loſing the time? Here is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for Magiſtrates to looke vnto who are to be deſired to heare by our actes &amp; exerciſes of learning how we go forwards: and if they find vs not as the ſonnes of the prophets but ſonnes of Beliall, to thruſt vs out of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:20947:17"/> &amp; giue our places to thoſe which will be better then we. O Lorde kindle in vs the feare of thee that for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues diligently in our vocation, in thoſe ſtudies whereby we may profit in the knowledge of thee: That abandoning al vaine delights which as the lightning are ſoone extinguiſhed, we may ſet our mindes &amp; ſtudies vppon ſuch thinges as may ſerue to the ſetting forth of thy glory through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            <p>Becauſe of the ſingular &amp; notable zeale co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the praiſe of God in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation which Dauid profeſſed &amp; promiſed in the firſt verſe, I haue entred the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole Pſalme to ſe the reaſons &amp; cauſes, the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; proues which Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid had. Wherfore ſo to ſtir vp al his wits &amp; all his hart and ſoule in this ſonge. The laſt time ſpeaki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the 2. verſe at the which this praiſe of god beginneth, &amp; as it were begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this anatomye at the head, &amp; looking nearely eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the beginning &amp; infancy of Dauids zeale, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering the firſt ſcholes &amp; maſters which he had, I fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al in this verſe: <hi>Great are the works of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> For here the Prophet fetcheth &amp; draweth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as from the furtheſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines this prayſe of God. Now it followeth in this third verſe.
<pb facs="tcp:20947:18"/> 
               <hi>Praiſe and glory are his workes, &amp;c.</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth vnto vs the ſame doctrine of the praiſe of the workes of God which we did ſee in the former verſe. For in theſe two ſentences he comprehendeth that knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God which may be vnderſtoode out of the creatures of God in the whole world, but he ſpeaketh here more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly &amp; diſtinctly of that knowledge which may here be learned of thoſe which looke diligently for them and delight in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of them. For it is requiſite both becauſe we are dimme of ſight &amp; the Lorde workes haue like the courtaines of Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their beautie within,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant. cant.</hi> 1.41.</note> that we hold our eyes neare vnto them and put our heades as it were within them to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider them if we will ſee thoſe things in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which Dauid a moſt excellent interpreter noteth and poynteth at <hi>Praiſe &amp; glory, &amp;c.</hi> Let vs firſt examine this that he ſayth: praiſe and glorye, &amp;c. the meaning of the Prophet is that the Lorde hath in ſuch wiſedom &amp; counſell made his works that euen by them may appeare to al that conſider them the praiſe and glory of the Creator, which doctrine he had in the verſe before declared but not ſo clearly &amp; manifeſtly: for here he expoundeth what he ment before when he called them <hi>great
<pb facs="tcp:20947:18"/> or excellent,</hi> that is full of the praiſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme of the maker, perfect maiſters of Gods wiſedom, excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teachers of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; moſt ſufficient witneſſes of his praiſe. This doctrine although it was declared partly before in the expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the former verſe, yet it may not be either tedious to you nor greuous to me ſome thing more to ſpeake of the ſame, ſeeing the holy Ghoſt vouchſafeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſtand vppon it. And we may thereby vnderſtand that the doctrine of the praiſe of God taught by his workes is not lightly &amp; ſmally to be eſtemed, ſeing the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God witneſſeth it vnto vs by repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. True it is that the word of God is the hie and principall maiſter of the knowledge of God in the Church of Chriſt as we ſhall ſee in the next verſe, the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple wherein his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye moſt appeareth: but notwithſtanding theſe are helps appointed of God to the ray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing of our mindes to his glorye, mouing vs being bodies with bodily things &amp; therfore vnles we be forgetfull of our weakenes, we may not neglect the ordinary meanes. The Prophets &amp; holy men of God whoſe loue &amp; zeale of the Lordes glory is left for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, haue labored in them &amp; profited by them to the praiſe of God. Let vs therefore followe them and namely Dauid in this
<pb facs="tcp:20947:19"/> place, Let vs followe the ſame ſteppes and wayes which he hath trode before vs: Let vs ſtande with him as it were in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the worlde, and lifte vp our eyes to heauen, and after caſte them downe vpon the earth: yea lette vs beholde euen our ſelues with thoſe eyes which we ſee Dauid to haue done in the 139. Pſalme. ſhal we not then be amazed and aſtonied at the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome we ſhal finde in them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.</note> and giue glory to the Lorde? ſhall we not in meditating but of our ſelues, finde a world of notable &amp; excellent works of God? Let vs looke but a litle aboue vs into that ſhoppe of the Lords notable works, where he maketh the rayne, hayle, and ſnow, lightning &amp; thunder, and conſider from whence he ſendeth rayne, howe he hath powred it as into barrels or bottels till we neede it. Conſider aboue that, the light of the ſunne, the moone, the number and order of the ſtarres, the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of the heauens, that fayre and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent courtayne whiche the Lorde hath drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer vs, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo the power of winds, the multitude of waters, and the ſtretching out of the ayre, the nature of beaſtes, the fruits of the trees, the ſmell of flowers, the beauty and property of ſtones, the vertue of herbes and of rootes, and in a worde
<pb facs="tcp:20947:19"/> the whole earth and the heauens, with all their hoſtes and furniture: Haue they not as it were written and grauen vppon them in great and text letters prayſe and glory to the Lord our Creator? In the 19. Pſalme the Prophet attributeth this ſame voyce of glory to the heauens:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1</note> The heauens (ſayth he) ſpeake the glory of God. &amp;c. and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that noble and ſwifte grant the ſunne the meſſenger of the ſame worde to all the world.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 104.2.</note> In the 104. Pſalme he compareth the light to a robe of glory and honor that the Lorde couereth him ſelfe withall, becauſe the light declareth manifeſtly all the works of God which are glaſſes of his prayſe. And in the 148. Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.</note> he putteth this ſong of the prayſe of God into the mouth of all creatures, euen of the hilles and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, of the ſoules of the ayre, trees of the wodde, of the dragons and wormes that creepe vppon the earth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 38. <hi>and</hi> 39. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 40.</note> So in the thirtie eyght and nine chapters of Iob, the Lorde to the ende that he might humble Iob, and bring him to the knowledge of the prayſe of God and his owne confuſion, he reckoneth the works of his hands in order, euen the heauens and earth and beaſtes of the fielde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 40.5.</note> And in the fortie Chapter he byddeth Iob likewiſe to decke him ſelfe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20947:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20947:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20947:21"/> with glory and maieſtie, and to array hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe with beautie and excellencie, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to make ſuch workes in whiche there may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appeare his prayſe, and renowme. Prayſe therefore and glory is his worke, ſo that where ſo euer we caſt our eyes, whether before vs or behinde vs, aboue or beneath vs, or within vs, on the right hande or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the left hande, all are full of the glory and prayſe of God: euen as our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34.</note> forbidding to ſweare by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens or earth, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any the leaſt creature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the Lordes ſeate, and this is his footeſtoole, and ſeeing we can not make a very heare, we muſte confeſſe that euen there alſo is a marke and token of the Lordes glory and maieſtie. Wherefore let vs with this wiſe and godly Prophet learne the beginning of our prayſing of God euer at theſe creatures, and knowe that it ſhal be ſhame and ſinne for vs to be dumme, when they are ſo hye and loude: but moſte of all to ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grieuous condemnation, if wher they declare the glory of God, we bring by ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e wickedneſſe, by oure vayne and vngodly behauiour, ſhame, reproche, and ignominie to his name. It followeth, <hi>And his goodnes remayneth for euer.</hi> I tranſlate the worde ſo: although it properly ſignifieth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20947:21"/> righteouſnes, becauſe I thinke that to be the Prophetes meaning. For in the next Pſalme the Prophet hath this halfe verſe in the ſame wordes ſpeaking of the good and mercifull man whoſe goodnes is not ſoone dried but continueth for euer, that is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.3</note> all his life.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.14.</note> So Daniell exhorteth Nabuchad. to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme his ſinnes by mercie &amp; liberalitie, &amp; yet vſeth this word of iuſtice. Here therfore the Prophet likewiſe meaneth the goodnes and liberalitie &amp; mercie of God which may be learned alſo out of his verie ordinarie &amp; common workes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.</note> This peece of the verſe is notably enlarged by the Prophet Dauid in the 136. Pſalme where he attributeth the creation of heauens, of the ſunne &amp; moone, of the ſtarres, of the day and night, of the placing of the earth vpon the waters, to the euerlaſting mercie of God: making this the ground &amp; foote of the Pſalme or ſong: For his mercie indureth for euer. And our Sauiour Chriſt alſo teaching his diſciples to be good to their enemies bringeth in thexample of God the father whoſe ſunne and raine ſhineth and falleth vpon his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies alſo.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.45.</note> Where we ſee this doctrine of the Prophet confirmed &amp; expounded, that is, that the creatures of God are witneſſes vnto all the world of his mercie and louing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20947:22"/> bindneſſe. In this ſenſe are the Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be expounded, when they ſpeake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the darkeninge of the Sunne, for the meane not that the Sunne ſhall fayle a fall but onely by that whiche is vnto vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a teſtimonie, and token of Gods mercie when it ſhineth they deſcribe the greatne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of troubles and confuſsion of all things to come when the Lorde ariſeth to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce of ſinne, which ſhall be ſo grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and horrible confuſion as if the Sunne were fallen out of heauen. This goodnes of God is not onely manifeſt by the Sunne &amp; thoſe excellent and high creatures, but euen as I haue ſhewed in the laſt verſe, his glory al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appeareth his mercie and goodnes euen in the leaſt of all creatures: not only toward vs for whoſe godly vſe he hath made them, but alſo to them ſelues. For firſt it is great goodneſſe to them in that they are: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlie it is great glorie to them in that they are the workes of the glorious and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall God: But eſpeciallie and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallie this goodneſſe of God is towarde vs in all creatures, that in the vſe of them we may thankefullie and humblie acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the exceeding mercie of God. The earth that we treade vpon, the houſes that we dwell in, the ayer which we liue by,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20947:22"/> the breade which we eate, and water or wine which we drinke, the fire that we warme vs by, the clothes which we wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and to be ſhort, all the creatures of God which we applie to our vſe, ought to leade vs to, and admoniſh vs of that goodnes and mercy of God, by whoſe onely bountifull grace and mercy we take and vſe them: without the feling and knowledge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which mercy of God, who ſo euer thou arte that vſeſt any creature of God, thou ſtealeſt it. The bread and drinke which thou deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt is worſe then poyſon vnto thee: for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we riſe to the conſideration of the loue of God towards vs, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a father towards his children, who prouideth theſe thinges for vs, by what right can we thinke that they pert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine vnto vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We ſee there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e that they are no leſſe witneſſes of Gods mercy, then of his glory and prayſe: And that who ſo euer ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yſe to accuſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lorde of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueltie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, maye be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ntly by the creatures of God command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d. And howe can not they be aſhamed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>laye this vppon the Lords, from whoſe onely good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and mercy it commeth that the world is, and we and all thinges hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him lyfe and beeing and mouing. But the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath more excellently deel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:20947:23"/> to vs by his creatures, as the Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by this noteth in that he addeth [and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth for euer.] No man can denie but that the Lord had ſhewed great mercy and loue towards vs if he had made this world like vnto a ſtage, and brought vs in for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, and after a whyle as it were to haue taken downe the ſtage, and ſo with the clapping of handes to haue gone away agayne. If he had made the vſe of all his excellent and noble creatures, the Angels the Sunne, the Moone, and the Starres, the heauen and earth, and all their ornaments for a yeare, a moneth, a weeke, or a day, who can denie but the Lorde had done vs great honour and worſhippe to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe vs the vſe of them? Yea if he hadde brought vs into the worlde but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſette vs on a pinnacle to haue ſeene theſe heauens and this earth, to haue ſeene the creatures of God according to their kinde, the benefite had bene great, and the grace and fauour more excellent then can be vttered. But howe hath the Lorde commended vnto vs his grace and fauour, his loue and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rcy, in that he hath made them permanent and durable, &amp; not like the ſmoke that per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>eth, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lyke the graſſe that groweth vp, and ſtraightwaye
<pb facs="tcp:20947:23"/> withereth, but like the trees of eternitie whoſe rootes are ſtayed and nouriſhed for euer. This grace and mercy euen to Adam in his perfection had bene worthy conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall prayſe and remembraunce, howe muche more nowe in this ſinnefull and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable lyfe? For let vs examine and trie our ſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let vs laye out liues to the rule of the Lawe of God, let vs looke and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde them in that glaſſe which r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th all thinges, and ſeeing we haue the vſe of theſe creatures by no other condition but by the obedien e of Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, what grace and mercy may we ſee in that they are not euery moment taken away from vs. I maruell that the ſunne which is witneſſe of ſo great and innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable faultes vppon the earth ſtandeth ſo long in the heauens: that the heauens melt not for the infection that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n them by our corruption: and that Ieſus Chriſte commeth not to burne them &amp; the earth ſo polluted with our ſinnes, to make that newe heauen &amp; that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>we earth wherein righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſhall dwell. Which of vs is he that perceiueth not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe out of him! If as out of a filthy bottomleſſe pitte, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> &amp; infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that were able to darke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſunne and couer al the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of y heauens that may
<pb facs="tcp:20947:24"/> not iuſtly wonder at the Lordes mercy i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the earth is able to beare vs ſo laden with vngodlineſſe and vnrighteouſneſſe? O Lord thy mercy reacheth vnto the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 57.10.</note> &amp; thy goodnes vnto the higheſt heauens. Thy pity and compaſſion is infinite &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, and yet who is he that conſidereth theſe things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thus I will leaue the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the mercy of God in this parte to your godly meditation, and come to the more n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e and perfect ſight &amp; knowledge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God which appeare th m h s Church on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you by the gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God and lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>member ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uens and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing all things in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m are ours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God they continue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vſe, that we ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s as thapoſtle her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eth, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the loue of his worde and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in all thing o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bedient to God. Thus we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the glory &amp; mercy of God out of the creatiues which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> witneſſes thereof in the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> world, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> only one place, but al th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whole world may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his glory &amp; mercy in euery part therof but yet if we compare this knowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20947:24"/> the glory &amp; mercy of God lerned here out of his creatures, to that which may be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen out of his Church &amp; out of his worde, we ſhall perceiue that in the creatures we ſee but his backe &amp; hinder parts, we ſee him but da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly as in a glaſſe of ſteel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but as in the nether &amp; outward courtes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, here in the church we ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as in the holieſt place of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the place of the oracl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, is n a gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall, and as it were face to face Wherefore let vs draw neare &amp; come vnto the temple, let vs looke into this glaſſe and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hold his fatherly countenance. <hi>He hath made t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nderfull worke remembrances.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in this verſe ſheweth the paſſing and wonderful work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he hath done for his Church, &amp; the exceeding loue that he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to his church. For although we haue already ſeene the mercy &amp; goodnes which he hath declared aſwel to them as to other euen in the verſe of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon creatures, yet becauſe they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to others with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the particuler &amp; priuate loue which the Lord beareth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, doth not ſo clearly appeare. Therefore here the Prophet beginneth a Catalog, although not with many words, yet full<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring all, and calling them to minde b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> generall
<pb facs="tcp:20947:25"/> wordes. And firſt that this ſpeciall and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ular care which he hath of his Churche may be knowen to paſſe the common and vniuerſall order of things, I thinke it may be noted out of the conferences of the words. In the ſeconde verſe he ſayth, <hi>Great are his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rkes, &amp;c.</hi> Here he vſeth a greater worde, and ſayth, they are wonderfull, for although this Prophet in other places call the common workes of God wonderfull, and are ſo in deede in them ſelues conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with theſe they are great, and theſe wonderfull ſo in halfe of the third verſe he ſayth, his goodnes remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, &amp;c. But here he vſeth wordes which ſeeme to come out of the Lords heart and bowell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s gracious and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>full: and he doubleth them, becauſe his loue is double and triple and manyfolde vpon them. This greatnes of the woders of God he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in theſe words, <hi>He hath made the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance or memoriall of them, &amp;c.</hi> Not that the goodnes of God which riſeth out of his creatures is to be forgotten o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> negligently to be regarded, for we know therefore the Lord in the beginning to haue inſtituted the Sabboth for a perpetuall memory to vs of his great loue, &amp; goodnes, &amp; mercy, and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dome, which appeareth in the world: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:20947:25"/> Dauid hath alſo made diuers Pſalmes in their reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, whereof ſome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that of the Sabboth was ſong in the temple.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.</note> But he ſpeaketh after an excellent ſort, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally &amp; chiefly giuing remembran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as if that in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, thother be forgotten. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the Prophet ſpeaking of the benefite of the deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rather reſurrection of the Iewes out of Babilon, ſayth that it ſhall no more be ſayd then, the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ueth which brought the children of Iſrael out of Egypt, but they ſhall ſpeake of the Lord thus, the Lord liueth which brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght them out of Babilon, meaning that this ſhall be ſo excellent, that in reſpect thereof the former (although ſo notable and as it is here alſo thus highly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended ſhould be no more ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, ſo in this place the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites which he hath ſhewed to his Church in their deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, after a ſort maketh the other to be forgotten.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 60.19</note> And Eſay ſpeaking of the light of the Goſpel in the kingdome of Chriſt, ſaith, that in that day the ſunne ſhall giue no light, nor the moone appeare: mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alſo that in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light which ſhal be ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of the ſunne, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſunne ſhal be darkned as the moone at his preſence: ſo in this place the lord hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theſe his works ſo
<pb facs="tcp:20947:26"/> famous and glorious that the former bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite like the ſtarrs at the riſing of the ſunne are obſcured and hidden. For i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they were wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thy once to be ſpoken of, theſe are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ften times: if thoſe to be written with a pen in paper, theſe are worthy to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on and with an Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mant ſtone: if thoſe with the hand of a man, theſe are to be printed with the ſinger of God. For as high as the heauens are in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of the earth, ſo muche hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d magnified the meaſure of his graces and benefites to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Churche aboue the reſt of the ſonne of men. But l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t vs conſider particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly what they were. The Prophet mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſignes &amp; wonders which the Lord declared by the hand of Moyſes and Aron in the middeſt of the lande of Egypt vpon Pharao and al his ſeruantes, the turning of the water into blood, the deſtroying of trees and fruites of the earth by the caterpillers, the filling of the lande full of frogges and hee, &amp; thoſe other which are written of by Moyſes the 9.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.</note> of Exod. and repeated in the Pſalme. 78. but aboue all theſe, he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth the cauſe and the occaſion of all theſe the na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tie, and as it were the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church, which was a greater &amp; more excellent worke then the making of
<pb facs="tcp:20947:26"/> the whole world. For the heauens &amp; earth as ſayth the Prophet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 102.26</note> ſhall waxe olde and periſh, but his fauour &amp; grace to his church ſhall endure for euermore. Therefore the Lord in reſpect of Ieruſalem ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the whole worlde, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay in the perſon of God reaſone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with that proude Sanacharib, who thought that he could as eaſily haue one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Ieruſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he had done Samaria and the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 36 19. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.26.</note> Haſt thou not heard (ſayth the how I haue tourmed it of olde, not naming but meaning and emphaticall; noting Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 49.23.</note> whom he preferreth before all the whole worlde. And the prophet Eſay pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pheſieth that the kinges and Monarches of the earth ſhall like the duſt of her feete, thereby noting what honour ſhe ſhall be in euen with her enemies. Seeing then the preſeruation of her, as appeareth, is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the eyes of God, that in the reſpect therof he conten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neth al things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng and birth of it muſt needes be the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eateſt &amp; moſt excellent worke that euer was, and therfore the remembrance of it, &amp; all thoſe ſignes &amp; wonders which the Lord wrought for it, turning the whole courſe of nature for his Church, ought perpetually to be with care and diligence celebrated.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20947:27"/> So Moyſes wondreth at it &amp; ſayth, was eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the like heard that God ſhould come to a people &amp; take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of another people in ſuch ſignes &amp; tokens &amp; wonders?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.34.</note> The Lord therefore hath printed the memorie of his maruelous works, ſo that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. Nay Egypt ſhalbe a witneſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to generation for euer, that the grace of God to his Church paſſeth all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. This marke ſhall remayne for euer, which the Lords mighty hand &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked arme printed &amp; ſealed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his enemies by ten ſtrokes. The Prophet by this kind of ſpeaking exhorteth all Iſrael, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath ſo maruelouſly deliuered, to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber theſe works, &amp; tell them further with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as in diuers Pſalmes. This doctrine therefore of the remembrance of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes &amp; benefites of God is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be declared. For if euer there were nede to ſpeake of it, behold the dayes of ioy and gladnes, of ſecurity &amp; eaſe, of ſport and play, and of piping &amp; dauncing, of riote and wantonnes, euen the dayes of forgetfulnes of Gods benefites. And if euer there were feare of the fulfilling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> propheſie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Iewes, that being ful they would forget the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.10.</note> as Moyſes propheſied, this is the day &amp; howre that Moyſes, as if he had ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20947:27"/> ſo long before, propheſied euen of vs. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of vs ſitteth vnder his vine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his figge tree in his ſeeled and garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed chamber, and the troubles that are ſo greate and manye bothe in our owne countrey and abrode, they touch vs not by Gods mercy. And why haue we all this caſe of God? to abuſe our time &amp; other benefits? or rather to remember them perpetually, and vſe them lawfully to the prayſe of god. This is therefore our time of daunger, our time of forgetting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes of our God, our time of falling away from the Lorde. If you the Lordes miniſters and watche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men make it not your time of care &amp; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of holding and ſtaying vs, of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring and repeating, and night and daye remembring and repeating the goodnes of our God vpon vs, his ſtatutes and his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, his lawes and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements which he hath appoynted for vs to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what daunger are we in? Therfore I wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der and maruell at it, that you ſee not the ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery places we ſtand on, and ſeeke to helpe vs. The goodnes of God hath ſo prouyded that in this Colledge there might be euery morning at prayer a Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euery euening w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prayers a ſermon, euery ſonday of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone &amp; afternoone together with prayers
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20947:28"/> the word of God preached, that the words of God perpetually ſounding in our eares, maye make this Colledge as it is called Trinitye Colledge, to be named the Lorde is there. There be thirteene places ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Preachers, beſide thoſe that are not accompted for the houſe: and yet this is not done, whereas I am perſwaded that three doing their office in care &amp; zeale, in godlines &amp; faithfulnes, were able by Gods grace to make this Colledge together with the Magiſtrat a Colledge of Saincts, a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge where no blaſphemer, no idle, no pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phane perſon, no ſonne of Belial, no Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite could be found, And if ſo many can not in their courſe maintaine this order in prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching, how many wil doe it? Is there any i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the places that are vnworthy, that are not al able? the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let the booke &amp; licence be takes out of his hand &amp; giuen to his fellow that is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he. I am ſure there is none of the wiſe &amp; godly ſort, but wiſhe and deſire that which I ſay. For as the benefits of the Lord are perpetually &amp; euerlaſting, ſo ought alſo the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of them to be, but there be men of corrupt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, wicked childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vngodly &amp; prophane perſons which conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them ſelues with a face or viſard of religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who know not what it is to ſerue God, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20947:28"/> will ſecurely deride this and laughe it to ſcorne. Wel the Lord would haue his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits to be remembred, let vs looke how we remember then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but it were an infinit thing to ſpeake of all: let vs conſider the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce but of this one wonderous &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous benefit euen the greateſt that euer was, God manifeſted in the fleſhe. This I ſpeake of, admoniſhed by this time, of the feaſt of the Natiuity that the worde which was ſpoken the laſt daye, may ſtande in the mouths of two witneſſes.<note place="margin">They which remember the fearfull example that fell out after in that Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas as we call it, may witnes that God by his ſeruaunts following direction of his word, threatneth not in vain</note> And if neither you of your ſelues neither at the word of God wil giue place, I pray God that a terrible &amp; heauy iudgement be not the third witnes of this truth vnto vs. Hath Ieſus Chriſt comen into the fleſh to lay the bridle of our necks to runne after our vayne deuiſes? hath he obtayned by his comming twelue dayes of God the Father for carding, diſing, and lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, for masking and mumming, for mocking &amp; mowing, for crying and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the practiſing of euery vayne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe that commeth to our heades all the yeare, or doe we thinke that this propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſo holye a thinge, this mocking of ſo earneſt a matter, this t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rning of the grace of God into licence and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that it ſhall be vnpuniſhed? what
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20947:29"/> is this but euen to giue a reede into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hande of Ieſus Chriſt, and to mocke h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> kingdom? What crowning of him is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this vayne mirthe and wantonneſſe, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with bryers and thornes to pricke his head Is this the ioye ſpoken of by the Angel that came to declare his birthe? tolde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tydinges of this gladnes? Is this the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite that thou haſt purchaſed to vs by the wonderful miſterie of thyne incarnation of Emmanuel? oh I am aſhamed that it ſhould euer be hearde of amongeſt the Iewes an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Turks, that the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at that time of the yere whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Sauiour was borne, giue the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelues for many daies fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ordinary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt &amp; ſhamefaced behauiour, from walki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ordinarily in their vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſtudies, to v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> modeſt &amp; ſhameful practiſes, to watching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> waking, &amp; al for vaine &amp; vnfruteful works <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> darknes. Wherin differeth our celebratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the natiuity of Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the popiſh Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas? that it ought to differ as farre as hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> euen the higheſt heauens from the nether moſt hel. Howe doe we looke to call Papi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from their vaine conuerſation, when we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not our ſelues a foote fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them? Is this th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conuerſation that ſhall ſtrike men with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> admiration and loue of vertue?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1.</note> If it be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quired of women ſo to behaue them ſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:20947:29"/> that other may be wonne thereby to God, doth it not more appertaine to men who were firſt made to Gods glory? but ought it not yet more to appeare in ſchollers &amp; thoſe which are called ſchollers of the holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. I thinke if but thus much were ſpoken amongſt the Heathen againſt ſo great an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, they would repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſackcloth &amp; aſhes. And yet I know that this people will not be brought from this vaine conuerſation, for they loue it &amp; delight in it, &amp; wil hide it and keepe it as a iewel. For without theſe things they complaine that it is but a dead Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas. Theſe men will neuer confeſſe the truth of this doctrine, till God haue ſealed it with ſome plague or other. Well thus we ought not to remember the benefit of that vnſpeakeable miſterye, by the which we are ioyned to God and God to vs, but in ioy of the ſpirit that vttereth forth Pſalmes and Hymnes, &amp; ſpiritual ſongs, and ſuch l ke.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 3.16</note> We ought alſo to keepe in mind not this onely, but all the other miracles which the Lorde wrought for the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſafgard &amp; benefit of his Church, ſo that our harts ſhould be like the arke of witnes: wherin as ther was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned for a perpetuall remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, a pot or cruſe of manna &amp; Arons rod for an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtig witnes of the care of G d for the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.4.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20947:30"/> of his Church: &amp; miracles, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> teſtified his election of Arons poſteritie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to haue in our harts all thoſe thinges which the Lord either worketh for all the church or particularly for any part thereof. In the reſt of the verſe he rendreth a reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe ſo great mercies: euen the Lords p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not deſert,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 33.19. <hi>Rom</hi> 9.15.</note> but as he ſayth to Moyſes: I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue mercy on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I will haue mercy: ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king his mercy the cauſe of mercy. So here his pity is made the cauſe, and he vſeth tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wordes doubling it, becauſe his mercye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> manifold toward his.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.6</note> Ezechiel in his 16. cap doth notably ſet out this pitie &amp; free grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Lorde toward this people in compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring him ſelfe to a man that ſeeing a poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> helples child new borne without any help<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of midwife or other, wallowing in her blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of very pitie and compaſſion waſheth as clenſeth her: doth all thinges needefull ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſuccour of it in ſuch a caſe: he then a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter bringeth her vp feeding and cheriſhin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her til the be mariageable: he then clothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her with all coſtly aray, and ſetteth her o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with all precious iewells, and caſting hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loue vppon her taketh her to be his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> as more at large is to be ſeen: in that place It followeth: <hi>He hath giuen a praye, &amp;c</hi> In the verſe going before we haue ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:20947:30"/> the exceeding loue of God towardes his Church teſtified by ſo many and ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeales as he declared in the land of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt. Where for the deliueraunce of the Church, he chaunged the whole courſe of nature, &amp; as it were in the bringing forth of a more excellent &amp; precious thing then the whole world which was at a worde made &amp; furniſhed, he did as it were many dayes in paynes &amp; trauels labour before the birth of the Church, ſo great a thing was it to make vnto him a Church. We haue alſo ſeene his onely pitie &amp; compaſſion to haue bene the cauſe thereof. Nowe it followeth in the fift verſe: <hi>He gaue a pray &amp;c.</hi> For although in the ſcripture ſomtime this word ſignifieth a por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion or a part, as in the 31. of the Prouerbs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.15.</note> yet properly it ſignifieth a ſpoile which a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on getteth for him ſelf, &amp; the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance of this place needes forceth this ſenſe. For he reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth the notable benefit of the ſpoile of Egypt what time they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: which although it may ſeeme at the firſt not to be ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or notable, &amp; not to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of particularly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other are not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally reckened, but together &amp; as it were in one word bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vp, yet we ſhal ſee this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not the only cauſe, why the prophet namely reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth it paſſing thother briefly,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20947:31"/> yet a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; iuſt cauſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.19.</note> True it is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> miracle of turning the waters of Epypt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> blod,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.6.</note> was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful &amp; a maruelous work. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if we maruel at the turning of ſix great po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of water into wine in the 2. of Iohn, what ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we ſay at the turning of whole riuers &amp; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taines from their nature? And if we ſee in a few quarts of water the finger of God, ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; arme of the Lord appeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> turning the great riuer, that great riuer N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus, &amp; all the waters beſides of Egypt, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fix earthen pots, but in ſixteene tymes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pots of wood &amp; ſtone?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 12.23.</note> And if in the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by lice or wormes the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful power of God appeared, what and how maruelous is the power, that made ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many as were able to deſtroy a mighty king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; innumerable people for if the ſtriking with botches &amp; ſores of one man: &amp; deſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his catle aſtoniſheth vs in the 1.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Iob, at the ſtriking of all Egypt, both man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beaſt, how ſhall we be affected? or if in the blinding of one citye of Sodom,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.11. <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.23.</note> the marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous hand of God ſhewed it ſelfe, what is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be thought in the blindnes of al Egypt? The reſt of the miracles may alſo in like maner be ſet out by comparing other iudgement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God with them. But I let them paſſe. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider only the deſtruction of the firſt borne,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20947:31"/> both of man &amp; beaſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.</note> Could the Lord doe a more maruelous worke for the benefite of his Church, that would ſo pearce the hart of them as the deſtruction of their eldeſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, their might, the beginning of their ſtrength, &amp; the excellency of their powers? Could the Lord doe a more notable worke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fight for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen by the hand of his angel? What then meaneth the Prophet to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber this of the ſpoile of their goods omitting other ſuch fearful &amp; wonderful to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens as we ſee? we ſhal ſee in the next peece of the verſe a ſufficient reaſon. But yet in the very miracle and wonder it ſelfe, ſufficient cauſe why to remember it omittinge the reſt. For if we waye &amp; examine this ſpoile &amp; pray that the Lord gaue his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tances of the ſame, we ſhall find that great and mighty power to haue wrought herein, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the reſt. For reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the hate, the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous hate that they beare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iſraell, all the iniuries and wrongs which they did vnto them. Firſt their counſell ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for the deſtroying of their men childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priuily by the midwiues, then their open cruelty in deſtroying them, their exactions, their greeuous exactions, their anger, their fierce anger, their crueltye, their vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall crueltie, which all in a moment the
<pb facs="tcp:20947:32"/> mighty hand of God turned to kindnes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> loue, to gentlenes, euen kindnes, gentlenes and loue ſupernaturall.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 12.36.</note> For at a word and requeſt of the Iſraelites, all the Egyptian gaue vnto them their gold and ſiluer, ther iewells and ornaments, and whatſoeuer they had deare and precious. Yea I think if they had asked, they would not haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed them their owne eyes, ſo mighty and aboue nature the hande of God wrought that he turned in a moment euen in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> twinckling of an eye their harts, their ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; adamant harts into fleſhly &amp; waxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harts &amp; their eies, their Crocadiles eies that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſight would haue deſtroyed them, into te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der &amp; womaniſh eies: their hands, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther armed &amp; wat like ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, into liberal &amp; peace able hands: &amp; in a word he made of wolues lambs: of cruel Tigres, fawning doggs, an meeke doues, of fiery and flying ſerpent which worke in my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo notable<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo wonderfull as you may perceaue paſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> al thother miracles. For by our own ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cruell affections which neuertheleſſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtaied by the ſpirit of God in his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may well perceaue what ſtrength &amp; powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it needeth to reſiſt &amp; ouercome them. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ageth not with ſuch rage: nor Behe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth is not ſo ſtronge as the rage &amp; power<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 40.10.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:20947:32"/> of ſinne is which dwelleth in vs: ſo that maruel it is that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſtaied. Here in ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appeared the mighty hand of God, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that God that is able to ſtay the raging of the ſeas, &amp; fiercenes of cruel beaſts, that he not only ſtaied their hatred, but alſo turned it into loue and kindnes. Wherefore let vs ſerue God &amp; be not carefull what man can thinke and imagine againſt vs. Their harts are no leſſe in the hand of God to moue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to loue vs than to hate vs, but he leadeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the kings hart as eaſily to his purpoſe, as the water. So Ioſeph feared God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou</hi> 21.1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.38</note> and he gaue him grace with Pharao and al his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, although they knew not God. And Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid often times &amp; in a moment perceaued Saules loue &amp; deare affection, although o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times he was purpoſed to kill him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.46.</note> And to Daniell in the carying into captiuitie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Babel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 5.29.</note> the Lord gaue not only in the eies of Nebuchadneſer and Baltaſar his ſonne loue and fauour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.28.</note> but alſo with the Perſian kings Darius and Cyrus, although a poore priſoner. And the ſame Cyrus &amp; an other Darius and Artaſhaſta were bended by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God to loue &amp; further the interpriſe of Zorobabell, Nehemias, Eſia,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſdra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1.1. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.8</note> and the reſt that returned to the building of the temple of God. Seeing then the Lord hath ſhewed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20947:33"/> ſuche light to them that ſerue him, where they ſawe nothing but darkenes &amp; deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all good things, what ſhame &amp; ſinne, yea how great &amp; iuſt ſhall the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our fearfulnes be, if in the Church of God amongeſt them that profeſſe godlines with vs, &amp; who are alſo appoynted for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> praiſe &amp; reward that do well, if (I ſay) we d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not loue, embrace, and follow after god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Well, here appeareth then firſt in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miracle the hande &amp; power of God for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r comfort &amp; calling forward to the ſeruice of God. Here appeareth alſo a notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple for the profe of the doctrine of the iuſtice of God, who will not alwayes winke at the proſperitie of the wicked. For although the Egyptians had heaped riches &amp; gold, ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>els and ornaments of pearles and precio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtones which they had gotten by extorſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; exaction of the Iſraelits, or els by othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> couetous &amp; crafty waies, yet the pacient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>biding of the Lord, &amp; as it were the holdin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his peace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50.21.</note> as Dauid ſayth in the 50. Pſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall not continue for euer, but ſome ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he draweth the wicked vpon the high ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to be ſeene bothe of them that feare th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lorde, and alſo that follow the like wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and plucketh the praye out of their teeth, and giueth it to his children. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:20947:33"/> God comforteth his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſuch iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and feareth other by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 7.7.</note> So in the ſeconde of the Kinges ſeuenth Chapter, the Aramites left their tentes beſide Samaria, and the children of God had a pray veſſells and clothes, ſiluer and golde, corne and vittells, as it is ſpoken by the mouth of the ſeruauntes of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 27.16.</note> For Iob ſayth though the wicked ſhoulde heape vp ſiluer as the duſt, and prepare rayment as clay, he may prepare, but the iuſt ſhall put it on: and the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſhall deuide the ſiluer. And Salomon ſayeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 13.22</note> a good man ſhall geue inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce vnto his children, but the riches of the ſinner are layed vppe for the iuſt. And although this alway appeare not, yet many ſuch notable and excellent examples are in the Scriptures of Gods iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whereby he vpholdeth the faith of his children that there feete ſlippe not: and thoſe wicked ones and ſinners whom the Lorde lifteth vp all their life higher and higher, and are not in this ſorte ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, are alſo lifted vppe that the triall of our faith in ſuche tentations may be more precious, and theyr ruyne and fall the greater and more horrible. Yet as in the puniſhment of other ſinnes ſometime the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20947:34"/> Lord exerciſeth his iudgementes vpon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> earth, ſo here alſo: and leaueth other for the laſt iudgement as S. Paule declareth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24</note> ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſinnes are manifeſt before iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſome follow. And this (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath in an other place) is a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his iuſtice,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5</note> to be reueiled in the laſt day. Nowe let vs conſider the epithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or title which he geueth to them on who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he beſtowed this pray. The Prophet ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>He gaue a pray to them that feare him.</hi> He ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this title to all the children of Iſrael as though their name were the fearers of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.1</note> So we ſee in the firſt verſe that Dauid would praiſe the Lord in the congregation of the iuſt: meaning in the temple, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the children of God were gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: to teach them whom God hath called out of darknes into light, that they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led euen to his feare, to his ſeruice, to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to godlines, to ſobernes, to modeſtie to all partes of holynes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5.</note> Thus the Prophet Dauid in the 50. Pſal. in the perſon of God calling all the Iewes together before who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord would reproue the wicked &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men, (that notwithſtanding their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly liues yet tooke the name of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their mouthes) calleth them Sainctes. And thApoſtle S. Paule writing to the Romane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:20947:34"/> ſayth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.1.</note> Beloued of God [called Saincts] vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church of Corinth. [Saincts by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling] And to the Epheſ. he exhorteth them to pray with watching and perſeuerance for all Sainctes. And in the end of his Epiſtles, [the Saincts ſalute you. Euen as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaking of the reprobate, deſcribeth them by thoſe frutes and practiſes to the which the deuill hath framed them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.10.</note> My ſonne if ſinners doe entiſe thee &amp; ſay, come let vs lay in wayte for blood, and 1. Pſalme. Happie is he that is not conuerſaunt with the wicked, with ſinners,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1.</note> with mockers of al godly and profitable inſtructions, ſo that by thoſe names which the Scripture geueth vnto vs, we ſee our calling, we ſee the ende of Gods mercies and benefites beſtowed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs. Not as they which know not God, to feare no godly maieſtie, to ſerue no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power, to lead a careleſſe and diſſolute life, to walke in licence and wantonnes, to geue our mindes and bodies as ſeruauntes to ſinne and vanities, but in feare and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of him who hath powred his benefits vpon vs, in his ſeruice and will to walke all the dayes of our life. This we learne by this title of the faithfull which the Prophet ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to them: and becauſe it commeth to be ſpoken of againe in this Pſalme, I referre it
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20947:35"/> till then. Onely beſeching you that we lay our owne hartes in this balance, &amp; ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we anſwere to them or no. Alas I know before we be put in, what waight we haue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how light we ſhould be found, although we ſhoulde take euen any of the leaſt of Gods benefites to be wayed withall. Let vs onely remember this pray which the Lorde hath geuen vs and wrong it out of the handes and teeth of the Epicures and Papiſtes which enioyed theſe liuings before vs: our knowledge of the Goſpel is ſomthing more our light greater: our conuerſation no do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſomethinge better: But howe litle is ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowledge, howe obſcure is our light, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> farre is our godlineſſe from that we migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue knowne and attayned to, if we had loued the Goſpell of God with all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoules and all our deſires? Who is not g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to him ſelfe that in fewe yeares, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the yeares of a Maiſter of arte) he might haue gotten as much learning as we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly get in ſeuen yeares more added vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that in foure or fewer yeares, might not get all the artes that we attayne to commonlie in eight or nine yeares, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might not in a yeares ſtudie get ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Scriptures as we get not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeauen yeares? For we ſpende the good
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20947:35"/> tyme God geueth vs in feaſting often in the countrie, in bedde, in walkinge, in gaminge, in idle and vnprofitable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, that oftentimes a whole moneth together, ſome thinke not of any thinge but cunninge and rehearſinge of partes to play: and God knowes the leaſt time is geuen to our ſtudies, our profitable and frutefull, our godlye and honeſt ſtudies. In playing, we are of labour pacient whole nightes and dayes: In godly exerciſes for the encreaſe of our faith and knowledge, too too vnpacient to tarie a litle time: earneſt in vanities, ſlacke and ſlowe in prayers, and wearie in ſermon time, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, wiſe and ſwift in attayning thend of our deuiſes, but negligent, fooliſh and ſlowe to any good thinge, quicke in vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euill, but deafe and doltiſhe and not able at twiſe telling to perceiue a godly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: As Haſael or as the Roe of the fielde to ouer take a vayne man whome we propounde to vs to followe, but heauie as the ſande, and ſlowe as the wormes, or meſſengers of euill newes to followe a good and vertuous and learned example. And yet we ſay, wherein are we to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued? It is but for faſhions ſake or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we find a fitte phraſe in the Scripture,
<pb facs="tcp:20947:36"/> yet we may haue grace &amp; commendacions. An idle belly, ah prophane hart, ah Epicure, ah the depth and bottom of ſinne, my hart telleth me there be ſuch euill beaſts in the Colledge. Nay my eyes and my eares are witneſſes of this, &amp; my minde telleth me a great deale more, which the iuſt God will to the ſhame of theſe idle beaſts bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their heades as he hath done vppon ſome already. Wel theſe be the frutes of the Egyptians whoſe ſpoyle the Lord hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs to feare and ſerue him: which he will (if we hinder him not by our ſecuritie and careleſnes) make more plentifull with new bleſſings: or els as to this people will giue theſe and more too, (but to our condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,) onely for his promiſe ſake. For it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth <hi>[he wil alway remember his couenaunt]</hi> Here the Prophet noteth the cauſe of this benefit which the Lord beſtowed vpon the Iſraelits not their fathers deſeruings. For A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac and Iacob had their many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, as appeareth in the Scriptures: much leſſe their owne, being now as it were Egyptians, Idolaters, worſhippers of oxen, and calues, and ſerpents, and hauing forgot the God of their fathers, but for the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full couenant and promiſe which he made to Abraham their father, that after their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20947:36"/> bondage in a ſtraunge land foure ages he would bring them forth with great ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13.</note> Here is the ground of the ioy and comfort of the Sainctes euen the Lordes mercie in promiſing, &amp; truth in performing. We haue no other title to the leaſt of Gods benefites but euen his truth to clame them by: that the worlde ſhall be no more deſtroyed with water,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.11.</note> what aſſurance haue we that deſerue euery mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be ouerwhelmed with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: but onely his couenaunt, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his mercie he wil alway remember?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.29.</note> What certainty haue we for our reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to life but only the truth of Gods promiſe? Seeing we haue deſerued euen the beſt of vs to lye and rotte in the earth for euer. But O Lorde thy faith endureth for euer. Thou wilt for thy promiſe ſake haue mercie vpon vs, although our ſinnes, the bondes and chaines of our ſinnes are able to kepe vs in hell without redemption. It followeth in the next verſe. <hi>He hath declared the power of his workes vnto his people &amp;c.</hi> As the Lorde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth ſtil his bleſſings vpon his people, ſo the Prophet followeth the commendation of them. And as the Lord riſeth in mercie and fauour, ſo Dauid acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree ſpeaketh of them. The benefit of their deliuerance was as we haue ſeene wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20947:37"/> &amp; miraculouſly brought to paſſe. Theſe enriching more wonderfully: this which the Prophet now remembreth is more then the other. And therfore he ſayth <hi>the Lord ſhewed the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; power of his workes in giuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them the heritage of the Heathen.</hi> As if he ſhoulde ſay although thus wonderfully and miraculouſly thy hande O Lorde deliuered thy children, although ſo mercifullie thou broughteſt them forth in great ſubſtaunce, yet theſe were litle in thine eies, thine hand &amp; thine arme prouided for them, beſides all theſe a perpetual heritage. Let vs therefore examine this miracle &amp; ſee whether it ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth as the Prophet ſpeaketh. For therby ſeing the loue, the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der &amp; excedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g loue that the Lorde beareth to his Church, we may draw &amp; receaue great comfort if we alſo be of the ſame body. For the Lord did nothing then, which now he will not do for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or rather in more excellent &amp; notable manner. Firſt therefore conſider the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings of this people, their idolatrie, their euill luſtes, their many and ſundrie tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wherewith forty yeares together they prouoked the Lord their redeemer, by their vnfaithfulnes, their rebellion to their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, &amp; laſt of al their feare of theſe natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whom the Lord had already diſcomfited &amp;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20947:37"/> deſtroied in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; their deſire to returne into Egypt (that was to hell) againe, where ſo cruelly they had bene handled: Conſider all theſe ſinnes and many more which the Lord ſawe in their harts: And aboue all the miracles that we yet ſee, we ſhall wonder at this miracle of their bringing into the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of promiſe. Surely God is omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yet ſinne is able to cloſe his hand &amp; (I ſpeake in reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence &amp; feare) able to tye his armes that he geue nothing. His face is ſeuen times more fauourable &amp; gracious then the Sunne, yet vnfaithfulnes is able to hide &amp; couet it. His loue is fire in dede, but the waters of vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines are able to quenche it. His ſtrength is wonderfull for the deſtruction of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but our ſinne, our vnfaithfulnes, our wickednes, our rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, maketh him weaker then water. The Lord is a mighty Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pſon in dede, but our ſins are ſharper the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er wherby we weake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; (if I may ſo ſpeake) ſhaue the head of this great Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pſon our Iudge and defender. The Lord is inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.11</note> yet our vngodlines hath made him bin take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſoner. His nature is invulnerable, yet by our ſin we pearſe him. He is life:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zachar.</hi> 12.10.</note> &amp; yet by our vngodlines (I ſpeake an horrible thing) we ſlea him. Here is therefore the ſtrength of the Lord reuealed, that notwithſtanding
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20947:38"/> all theſe rocks and cragges as the Prophet Amos ſpeaketh the courſe of the Lords be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits was not hindred, his hands not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, his light not darkened, his loue not quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, his ſtrength not weakened, his wil no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing chaunged, it repented him not of his promiſe as in the dayes of Noah, &amp; that he made not an vtter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumption of this ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people. This may be well noted for the ſetting forth of this great benefit. Beſides this we may alſo remember the vnfitnes of this people for battle.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.18.</note> They had bene brought vp in kilnes among the bricks, they were accuſtomed to bearing of burthens for the building of the Egyptian piramides: not inſtituted or inſtructed in feates of warre, not armed, not politike, yet in this infirmity the Lordes ſtrength appeared: they were ſtraungers in the countrie and therefore eaſely ouerthrowne in vnknowne places they were but one people: their enemies cunning in the countrie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.7.</note> and ſeuen greater and mightier nations then they: they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in tents: their enemies in ſtrong &amp; walled townes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 13.29</note> whoſe walls reached vnto the heauens: theſe were footemen: their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies on horſes and iron chariots: theſe without weapons of warre, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther outward help which all their enemies
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20947:38"/> had in great abundance: yet for all theſe the hande of God brought them vnto the lande that he had promiſed and ſworne to their fathers. So that the miracles in Egypt and their ſpoyle may be forgotten, in reſpect of this great and wonderfull worke: Moiſes not ſpoken of in compariſon of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſua by whoſe hande the Lorde brought this worke to paſſe. In their deliueraunce he ſhooke the earth: but in their placing he moued the heauens.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 10.22.</note> The day was turned into night in Egypt: But here the whole courſe and order of the worlde both in the heauens &amp; earth was chaunged at the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Sunne, which as aſtoniſhed at this worke, at this great worke ſtoode and forgot to runne his courſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 12.29.</note> The firſt borne were but deſtroyed in Egypt, but all their children from the firſt borne to the childe in the wombe were here deſtroyed. There they were ſpoyled onely of their richeſſe and iewells: but here of their richeſſe and inheritaunce. There one Kinge was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: here the Lorde ſcattered many Kinges for their ſake, and made Iehoſuah to treade vpon their Kings neckes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane all their crownes. This did the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull zeale of the Lorde of hoſtes bring to paſſe for his promiſe ſake, and ſhewed as
<pb facs="tcp:20947:39"/> the Prophet ſayth euen his power and his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth in this worke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.</note> to giue his people the heritage of the Heathen. Seeing then the hand of the Lord brought all theſe thinges to paſſe for them, not only to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the iron furnace but to place them in a paradice, not to begin to be mercifull but to bring it to an end, and as the Prophet Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pareth it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.4</note> not only to cut the nauell of this woman child, to waſh it, to ſalt it, to ſay vnto it, liue euen in blood: to ſay vnto it liue, but to bring it vp, to forme her, to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion her, to decke her with ornaments, and to geue her an heritage, ſo large and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an heritage. What feare, what obedience what reuerence is there that ſhe ought not to geue to God her redemer that tooke her out of the iawes of death to be a peculiar, a deare, and beloued people aboue all the nations of the earth vnto him. He paſſed that Ladie of all the worlde, the Monarchis of Aſſiria ſo great in power, ſo excellent in glorie, ſo famous in victories, or what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nation or Kingdome ſo euer was fayre and excellent, he paſſed by them all to take vnto him out of Egypt ſtraungers, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, and ſlaues of Pharao vpon whom he woulde ſhowe his loue and mercies, Therefore let them and vs together with
<pb facs="tcp:20947:39"/> them magnifie the Lorde of heauen and earth, the God of Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, whoſe trueth remayneth for euer and praye that as to them he gaue ſuche benefites to ſerue him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.45.</note> to keepe his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and obſerue his lawes as Dauid ſayth, making this the ende of theſe wonders and benefites, ſo the power of his workes which he hath alſo ſhewed towardes vs in infinite and innumerable benefites, may worke an excellent kind of ſeruice, in the which, the power and the excellencie of the feare and worſhip of God may appeare to his glorie and our comfort Amen.</p>
            <p>It followeth in the 7. verſe: <hi>The workes of his hande are veritie and iudgement, all his fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es are true.</hi> I haue heretofore declared the wonderfull and notable workes which the Lorde executed in the placing of the people of Iſraell, in the land of the Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nits, Hitits, Hereſits &amp;c. and ſhewed by it, that which the Prophete ſpeaketh of the ſtrength of God: which benefit (as hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared) was to be accounted of aboue the other of the deliueraunce and pray of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt: which notwithſtanding were as I haue ſhewed wondrous &amp; maruelous workes. In this verſe the Prophet rendreth a reaſon of this wonderfull counſell of God. And firſt
<pb facs="tcp:20947:40"/> he declareth that it was ſo be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> by God appoynted. For he calleth the performance of it, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eth.</hi> And becauſe as fleſhe and and ſinne is prowde and quickely leapeth into the throne of iudgement euen ouer God him ſelfe &amp; his doings, (ſuch vile and abhominable deuills are we) The Prophet giueth a further reaſon when as he ſaith the works of his hands are iudgement. He ſaith not, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ger,</hi> leaſt any ſhoulde thinke cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in God. <hi>The workes of his hands are truth</hi> The Hebrewes vſe this worde when they ſpeake of a ſure and certaine performance of that which is promiſed. Therefore they ioyne theſe two words <hi>mercy and truth</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whether they ſpeake of God or man. Dauid praiſeth God for mercie and truth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.10</note> that is, for his mercifull promiſe and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true performance.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.29.</note> And Iacob ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Ioſeph to do this mercy &amp; truth to him, that he be caried to be buried in the land of promiſe. Theſe examples ſhall ſuffiſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I might bring almoſt infinit. But this is enough to vnderſtande the meaning of Dauid. Nowe that the worke was truth, we ſhall vnderſtand if we reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the notable promiſe which the Lorde made vnto Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, and confirmed it vnto Iſaac and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to Iacob that he woulde geue to them
<pb facs="tcp:20947:40"/> and to their ſeede after them the lande of theſe ſeuen nations.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.14.</note> For the Lord after that Lot was departed from Abraham, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Abraham dwelling in the lande of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan to lift vp his eyes and looke from the place he ſtoode in, to the Eaſt, &amp; the Weſt, &amp; the North, &amp; Sowth, &amp; promiſed to giue it vnto his ſede after him for euer. This was done fiue times to Abraham. And Abraham died and was buried in the land of Canaan. In the xxvj.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.24.</note> chap. the Lord promiſeth Iſaac to kepe the ſame oth that he ſware to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Abraham. And in the xxviij.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.13.</note> chap. the Lorde appeared to Iacob in the way to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopotamia in a dreame &amp; promiſed to make his ſeede alſo to floriſhe and to ſpread euen to the North and Sowth &amp; Eaſt &amp; Weſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was then a ſtraunger and alone. And the ſame alſo is in the xxxv.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.11.</note> chap. with this addition, that euen Kings ſhould come out of him. Theſe are the promiſes &amp; other which the Lord made &amp; bound him ſelfe to kepe to this people: which as we haue ſeene after 400. yeares, the Lorde accompliſhed. This truth which Dauid ſpeaketh of ſhal be more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; famous, if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider thoſe hinderaunces, which ſeemed to haue bene able to haue made all theſe promiſes vaine. Firſt conſider what daungers &amp; perills that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20947:41"/> Abraham was often in, being but one man, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iuen from country to countrie. And as Dauid ſaith both of him and of Iſaac and Iacob, they were driuen from one kingdom to an other people. And this came to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham what time he had no feede. So that by the enmity of the Philiſtians, by the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger he was in for his wife, the promiſe of God concerning his poſteritie was in great daunger.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.12.</note> Conſider the barenneſſe of Sara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſo many yeares after this firſt promiſe ſo that it might haue bene thought he had forgotten his promiſe. After this what was the condition of Iſaac in whom now all the hope of the promiſe reſted? howe farre of from death was he when his father had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſtretched out his hande for his death and that at the Lordes commaundement? where then ſeemed any hope of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or of this trueth that Dauid commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in this place? After this the barennes of Rebecca, which when it was taken away behold a newe hinderaunce. The children fought in her wombe together that ſhe was in great feare that thone woulde haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed thother. Then the feare of daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that Iacob was in of his brother Eſaw who had vowed his death. And after that he was returned out of Siria, when Simion
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20947:41"/> and Leui deſtroyed the Shecamites, what hope was there then that one of all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>cke ſhoulde haue bene left aliue? Which Iacob alſo feared, and had not that God of trueth (who to bring to paſſe his promiſe had before ſo miraculouſly preſerued his father from his enemies) as it were holden him vnder his arme and kept him in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, they had at that time beene all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. But the feare of them fell vppon the nations about them and they eſcaped daunger. Then followed alſo an other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie for the hinderaunce of his promiſe, euen the famine which was in the lande of Canaan nowe riſen as it were againſt the trueth of God. After that the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Egypt in whiche fornace muche more hotte then the fornace of Nebucad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſar, yet neuertheleſſe they were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. Theſe circumſtaunces conſidered which were as ſo many contrarie windes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this purpoſe of God, or like ſo many red ſeas to their entrance into this lande, or ſo many walls of iron &amp; gates of braſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe which they muſt breake before they coulde come into this promiſed city, Theſe circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances of hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I ſay conſidered, which notwithſtanding the great &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God for his promiſe ſake remoued, doe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20947:42"/> make the arme of the glory &amp; power of God ſo much more famous and glorious &amp; more greatly to be praiſed, neither that onely, but comfortable alſo vnto all that waite for his promiſes in faith and pacience. For here we ſee an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple drawn before vs by the finger of God to looke vpon, for the confirmation of our faith and hope, if we waite alſo for thoſe thinges which the Lord of his mercie hath promiſed to vs. We ſee that the Lorde hath promiſed that he will giue the Goſpell free paſſage in the kingdom of Chriſt. And this we looke for, &amp; all they whoſe harts are touched with the loue of the glorie of God waite &amp; looke for it till their eyes daſell in their heads. For we ſee mountaines, &amp; hills, ſeas, &amp; waters, kingdoms, &amp; peoples, Kings, Princes, and Counſelers of the earth, lift vp them ſelues &amp; ſtand againſt it: yet we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort our ſelues with theſe words, that the Lord of mercie is the God of truth and will bring this promiſe to paſſe as we ſee it begun this day. For we ſee theſe kingdoms of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, Denmarke, Germany, Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia and diuers other kingdoms which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Italy, Fraunce, &amp; Spayne, were as a Scepter or mace in the hand of the deuill of Rome, (as we ſe in tragedies in the hands of furies) we haue ſeene this mace although
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20947:42"/> for a time faire &amp; bewtifull with crownes &amp; gold in his hande, yet now almoſt burnt out of his hande. The fire of the Goſpell brake forth firſt one peece of his mace in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: then it cracked of this ſide and then of that ſide the ſea: and nowe it cracketh in Fraunce, and what is left in his hande but a ſtumpe of Italie and Spayne which the Lorde for his trueth and promiſe ſake will burne alſo out of his hande. Neither will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thus leaue. But I doubt not but as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Antichriſt of the Eaſt the Turke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan together with him, ſo he ſhall end toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and hope that when the man of ſinne is conſumed, the Lord wil alſo take his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of his hand &amp; accompliſh the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the elect. In Barbarie, Grece, and elſe where. And when Lord? how long ſhall thy foes triumphe ouer thee and make a mock of thy ſonne Ieſus our Sauiour whome we looke and waite for, for the deſtruction of theſe Tirants that haue lift vp them ſelues againſt him, and for the refreſhing of thy wearye and faintye children? Doubt ye not but the Lord numbreth the yeares of their captiuitie &amp; of their appoynted time for ſaluation, when our Redemer will come and fulfill all thinges which haue bene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and determined by the Lorde of truth.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20947:43"/> Thus may we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> comfort our ſelues in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Gods promiſes which becauſe it were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to folow, I wil reſt on this one exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. Which for all other may be a patterne to vs of the truth of God. For in this verſe is bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred againe to ſpeake of it. <hi>The workes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hands are truth &amp; iudgement &amp;c.</hi> This ſecond word which the Prophet vſed I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaid is added to correct our wicked iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt God, becauſe ſuch &amp; ſo great is our corruption, ſo venimous &amp; poyſenfull we are of nature y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent not our ſelues with equal enmities, but our ſinne breaketh out &amp; falleth vpon the iuſt and great God. Therfore the Prophet attributeth this title to the Lords works y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are no leſſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous &amp; iuſt, then they are true &amp; ſure. Now he meaneth in this place y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the puniſhments which he executed for his people vpon the Cananits &amp; Egyptians, were moſt righteous iudgements as we haue ſeene therefore the truth of God in theſe workes, ſo let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider now therin his righteouſnes. And firſt for the Egyptians. I diſpure not of the ſecret &amp; hid cauſes which are only knowne to the Lord. Why he ſet this people &amp; the other of Canaan aboue all other nations as it were vpon a ſtage in whoſe perſons this traged<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be ſeene, which can not be vniuſtly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20947:43"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the Iudge of heauen and earth, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of all the world, as Abraham ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25</note> but I will onely remember thoſe manifeſt &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed reaſons by the ſcripture which were the occaſion of al their puniſhments, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we may remember that Egypt moſt ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannouſly &amp; cruelly handled this people. Knoweſt thou not, oh vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kful Egypt, how to deale with thy patrons and benefactors? was the benefite thou haddeſt by Ioſeph forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in whoſe hand was thy life, &amp; in his wiſdome thy glory? in whoſe wil was thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, &amp; in his pleaſure thy ſhame? had ye forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law of nature, oh Pharao &amp; al thy Senators, &amp; al the people of the land of Egypt, ſo vncurteouſly and vngently to handle ſtraungers? Came they to be your ſeruants &amp; bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmen, or felows &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? &amp; yet ſaide, Come let vs take counſell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.10.</note> Knew you not laſt of al that they were gods people, his heritage, his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his prieſts &amp; kings, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſoeuer bleſſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3.</note> he had promiſed he would bleſſe agayne, &amp; curſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> curſed them? had not their God threatned &amp; ſmitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen kings for their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſakes Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Iſaac, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pharao &amp; Abimelech? had not Egipt a ſinguler benefit aboue all natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hoſts of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were ſo deare to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord? Were not they more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:20947:44"/> Nilus in her higheſt &amp; deepeſt inundations profitable to the encreaſe of the fruites of the land? The heate of the ſunne, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the ſtarres, &amp; all other benefites that are required for the ryping of their fruites, came out of no other heauen then euen this very people. For as the Prophet deſcribing the returne of the children of Iſraell out of Babilon, for whom the Lorde would digge fountaynes euen in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, turneth to the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; exhorteth them to prayſe God that had giuen waters in the wildernes, becauſe through the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this people it was alſo common to them: So theſe ſerpents &amp; tygers of Egypt receiue theſe bleſſings of God as by occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is, for his peoples ſake: their corne, their wine, &amp; encreaſe of all things, and yet they take counſell to ſlay ſome of them, and to kepe the reſt in perpetuall bondage. Iuſt therefore were theſe thy iudgementes, oh Lord, and righteous was all thy counſell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt this cruel &amp; vnnatural people. Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> turnedſt their waters into blood, becauſe they were a bloody people: thy hand ſtrok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with darknes, becauſe they were blind and ignorant of the benefites: They hande brought botches &amp; ſores vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they were full of ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n &amp; poyſon: frogges
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20947:44"/> and hee &amp; vermin were ſent amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them, becauſe they were a proud generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re depriued of their ſubſtance and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, becauſe they were gotten by cruelty and extortion: their firſt borne ſlayne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were the beginning of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſtrength: the king &amp; his hoſts drowned in the ſea, becauſe they were all malicious and obſtinate. The works therefore of thy hands in this people, were iuſtice &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nowe I will conſider the Cananites and declare the Lord my God to haue bin in their deſtruction alſo moſt iuſt and moſt righteous. This is ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> declared in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, when they ſhew Iſrael of their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, diuinations, crueltie, and ſuch like, for they ſay the lande is full of abhominations as it was in the dayes when the Amorites &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ittits dwelled in it. And Ezechiel decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all their wickednes in two words, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not their father, nor Saray their mother, but ſome Amorrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 16.3.</note> and ſome Hittite ſurely bare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whereby the ſinne &amp; abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this people are manifeſt. And if we looke for the lord in his owne perſon to giue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13</note> behold he appoynteth 400. yeres to paſſe ere the ſeede of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould enioy this land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the meaſure of the ſinne of the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites
<pb facs="tcp:20947:45"/> was not then full, their fruites <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ripe, the waters of wickednes not yet o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their heads, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very neare ripe, though not fitte for the harueſt. For the mercyfull and gracious God doth ſo long beare with the wickednes of the world till it reache to the very heauens: that his long patience (as thapoſtle teacheth the Romans) might driue them to the conſideration of it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</note> &amp; to repentance. But the Lord hath all that lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time that he ſpareth, his ballaunce in his hande, wherwith he wayeth the beginning and encreaſe &amp; full weight of their ſinne, &amp; then he caſteth them out. He conſidereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and wayteth for the ripenes, before he ſendeth meſſengers to plucke them of the tree, or cut them of the earth. He tarieth till they be dry and fit for the fire before he throw them in: till they be farre, before he ſlay them: till they be dry &amp; withered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he put the axe to hewe them downe. Therfore it is conteyned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture that the earth was full of ſinne when the Lorde ſent the flood &amp; deſtroyed the worlde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 6.5.</note> and made it as before the diſtinction of light &amp; darknes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 8.</note> almoſt for a yere. We reade alſo that the ſinne of Sodome was great, &amp; that the cry therof aſcended vp to the eares of the Lord of hoſtes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.20</note> Thus alſo the Lorde in a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20947:45"/> viſion of ripe apples ſheweth Amos y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of the Iſraelites deſtruction to be at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dore.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 8.1.</note> And our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth this long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ing of the Lorde by the parable of the husbandmen, who wayteth 3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 13.7.</note> yeres after no fruite came, to ſee if any fruite would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. But we ſee the lord not to haue way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted three yeres for the repentance of this people, or till they were ripe, Neither 120. yeres as in the dayes of Noy, But 400. yeres as he had declared before to Abraham. Therefore the works of his hands were not againſt this people vnpacient in anger or fury, but righteous in iuſtice &amp; iudgement. The ſword wherby they were ſlayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prince to al the people euen wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword of righteouſnes: &amp; the fire that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed their cities &amp; deſtroyed their houſes, was the fire of iudgement the hayle &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fought againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reaſon, iuſtice &amp; equiry. That God therfore deſtroyed the great &amp; ſmal, the old &amp; yong, &amp; as it is ſayd, the mother &amp; her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it was not cruell rage, not iniury, but right &amp; iuſtice, in ſtriki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt: &amp; patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſuffring in forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: finally great wiſdome in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leprous generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſt it ſhuld ſtil encreaſe: &amp; great mercy to his church. Thus the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appeareth not only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth &amp; faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:20947:46"/> workes of God in performing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which were ſo long ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bringing of his people out of Egypt and placing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Canaan, but alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wiſedome, and mercy. Nowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> halfe of this verſe which foloweth, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet teacheth that doctrine &amp; fruite which is here to be gathered. For he ſayth, all his ſtatutes are true, ſo that from theſe perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer promiſes and iudgementes of God, the Prophet ryſeth and reaſoneth for the ſurety of all Gods promiſes, whether they be for the deſtruction of his enemies, or benefites promiſed to his Church. For by ſtatutes it ſhould appeare by the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this place, that he vnderſtandeth all this.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore for the ſuretie of the workes of God in that behalfe (for after we ſhall ſee it in the other part concerning the benefites towards his Church) he ſayth all his ſtatutes are true: that is, all his appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted counſels are ſure and faythfull, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be a deſtruction and ouerthrowe of the wicked, or a comfort to the godly. And howe ſhall not they be moſt ſure and moſt truely performed, ſeeing they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by him, whoſe handes made the world and all that is therin, who hath done
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20947:46"/> what ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> he purpoſed &amp; was good in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe hand is the hand of power and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> almightie? Man in dede in vayne and deceiuable, and able to be hindered of that which he hath determined, but the lord the almighty God creator of heauen &amp; earth, in whoſe power are al creatures, euen kings and princes, and in whoſe handes are the chaynes and bitte and bridle, whereby the very diuels are at his word loſed &amp; bound, ſent out and called in agayne, is neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued nor hindred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bringing his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to paſſe. The waters of Tema &amp; Sheba,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 6.19.</note> as Iob ſayth, are with heate dried vp, ſo that they which looke for helpe at them, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and aſhamed; but the counſels of god are as l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing &amp; ſpringing waters, which ſhall continue faithfull and ſure &amp; vndried, though all the mountaynes &amp; fountaynes from whence the riuers and floods do flow, yea though the ſea ſhould be dried vp, for thoſe runne out of the earth, but the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of God flowe from his hande which no ſunne can drie, nor winde driue away, till al be fulfilled that he hath determined. They are therfore like the ſpringing waters, that is, continuall and durable: like the great mountaynes that can not be remoued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 125.1.</note> as ſayth the Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like the fielde that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20947:47"/> bringeth forth fruite, and can by no iniurie of weather be hindred: like the worde and commaundement of the Perſian kinges,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.12.</note> whoſe worde is ſure, as it is in Daniel or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like the Lord himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1.17.</note> who is immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnchangeable. Crye therefore and weepe, make a noyſe &amp; howle ye contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Lorde, ye that delight in your vanities, &amp; take pleaſure in that that is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malac.</hi> 4.1</note> for behold the day co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth that ſhall burne as an ouen, and al the proude, &amp; al that do wickednes, ſhal be as ſtubble, and the day that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſhall burne them vp, ſayth the Lord of hoſtes, and ſhall leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither roote nor braunch. Heare ye drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards and gluttons, ye Epicures, and idle bellies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 14.</note> and feare, for beholde the Lorde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth with thouſandes of his Sainctes, to giue iudgement agaynſt you of al the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes you haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, and of all the cruell words which wicked men haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken agaynſt his worde. For this is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ſentence of the mightie God, whoſe name is wonderfull and power mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous, whoſe decrees are ſure and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells vnfallible. This fearefull leſſon the Prophet teacheth the wicked and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable children, that diſhonour the glorious and be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cifull name of the Lord our God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:20947:47"/> when he ſayth, all his appoyntments or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees are ſure. For they may be ſure &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, they may perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; write of it, that the iudgement of God vpon them in what ſort ſoeuer the Lord haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether to their deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues or by other, whether immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen or by common death, or by ſome notable ſpectacle, or in what ſort or kind ſoeuer it be, that it ſleepeth not, but it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a chariot, whoſe horſes are the winds, &amp; whoſe wheeles are the whirlwinds euen ſpedily &amp; haſtily to their deſtruction. And now you that feare God &amp; delight in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, that frankely &amp; freely g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e your ſoules &amp; bodies to the Lords ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, that loue his word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, his glory, and his children, that indeuour with al your power in that vocation wherto you are called, to ſanctifie &amp; prayſe that holy name, that are in battaile &amp; field againſt temptations with ſinne, with the diuell, with the intiſementes of vanitie, that haue ſolde all things for the precious iewel of the Goſpel, &amp; delite your ſelues therin, that therfore bare the hate of the wicked, the mockes of the ſcornefull, the iniuries of the violent, that grone and mourne and lament, and ſight and weepe vnder the burden of ſinne &amp; power therof,
<pb facs="tcp:20947:48"/> that would raigne in our mortall bodies, let vs at this voyce of the Prophet when he ſayth all the Lords decrees are ſure, let vs, I ſay, lift vp our heades and paciently and ioyfully looke for that day when the Lorde ſhall deliuer vs and all our fellowes from al oppreſſion &amp; iniury of the wicked: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſhall no more watch agaynſt vs: when the power of ſinne ſhall not hinder the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God to haue his full and perfect worke in vs. That which foloweth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> verſe is only a repetition of this that I haue already expounded: for where hee ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the workes of his hands are truth, here more playnly he ſayth, <hi>They are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished for euer and euer.</hi> And where he ſaid, <hi>They were truth &amp; iudgement,</hi> he now ſayth, <hi>They are done in truth &amp; equitie.</hi> Therfore: is a doctrine moſt neceſſary to knowe the truth of God in performing his promiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his iudgement, &amp; equity in the ſame, ſei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Prophet ſo diligently noteth it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhort Pſalm he giueth two verſes to it, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting other thinges vp very briefly. Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> therfore for our ſeale to his truth &amp; iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of god in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l his works, what ſort ſoeuer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are of: and let them that know &amp; feare t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Lord, ſay alwaies the Lord is true &amp; right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to him be glory for euer &amp; euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20947:48"/>
            <p>I am come by the grace of God to the end of the Cxj. Pſalme, which nowe almoſte a yeare agoe I tooke in hand, wherein I haue ſpoken firſt of the proeme which is in the firſt verſe, ſtirring vppe him ſelfe to the writing of it to the prayſe of God: then of the double matter in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, both of the worke of God appearinge in the whole worlde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e they are witneſſes vnto vs and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the glorie and mercie of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor who is bleſſed for euer Amen: Then of his benefites beſtowed vpon his church, the creation of it, their deliuerance, their mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous deliuerance, their more miraculous enriching, &amp; their moſt miraculous &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull placing in the lande of their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. All, arguments of a moſt entire and tender loue &amp; affection that God had to his Church, and ſeueritie, iuſtice and truth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Egyptians and Amoheans as I haue declared. Nowe followeth the laſt and principall benefit that they receiued, to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of. <hi>He ſent redemption vnto his people, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded his couenaunt for euer &amp;c.</hi> This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is the declaring &amp; opening of the will &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements of the Lord vnto them. Of the which to ſpeake according as it is requiſite by proportion and meaſure of this to the other which they before receiued, I
<pb facs="tcp:20947:49"/> neede a more plentifull wiſedom, &amp; a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e gracious tonge which the Lord graunt me. For if in thother I haue ſpoken with the tongue of a man, in this I haue neede of the tongue of an Angell: For if we accompted of the other as precious, excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, of this, we ought to make much more accompt as by compariſon ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. And firſt for their deliuerance out of Egypt, you all are witneſſes what a notable thing it was, and how I haue laboured to ſet forth therein the hand and power of God, and his loue to his people in it: yet the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures doe lighten it in other places, as we ſhall ſee. For we read that the Lord did alſo bring the Philiſtines from Oaphtor, and the Syrians from Tire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 9.7.</note> as Amos declareth. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſee that their deliueraunce out of Egypt was no ſinguler or proper thing which the L. wrought for them more then for other. Alſo their placing in the land of Canaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſo notable as I haue before ſhewed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.9.</note> yet Moyſes ſheweth the like done for other people. The Iſraelits were placed in the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Canaan, the Ammonits and the Moabits thoſe inceſtuous ſonnes with their inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous generations were likewiſe placed in the land of the Zamzonuns. he deſtroyed the Enakymes, for Iſraell: likewiſe he deſtroyed
<pb facs="tcp:20947:49"/> theſe Za<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>zomias. For the Amonits, a people great &amp; tal as the En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>imes ſo the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied the Horymes &amp; brought in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonnes of Eſawe in their place, And the Attins w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> dwelt in Hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rim euen vnto Aza. Them, the Caphtorims deſtroied &amp; dwelt in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Where then is become the priuiledge of Iſraell or thoſe great workes for them, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> we magnified ſo greatly and highly before. What vehemence then is in this exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Prophets, where they euer bringe in their deliuerance out of Egypt, then pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, their vſe of the fructs which they planted not, corne which they ſowed not, and houſes which they builded not, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe haue bene no leſſe done for Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels then for his owne people? Surely it can not be denied but although their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance were commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them with other, yet the maner of their deliuerance was not able &amp; ſinguler. for ſo Moyſes ſayth, was it euer heard before that God ſhoulde come as it were from heauen to deliuer one people out of an other that oppreſſed them with ſignes and tokens and wonders as he did to them, as if he him ſelfe had bene op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with them? as if he had burned in the furnace with them? as if he had labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder their burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? as if he had fled out
<pb facs="tcp:20947:50"/> of the land with them? yet notwithſtanding all theſe thinges which were wrought for their deliueraunce, were both maruelous and ſinguler, yet they are but dead and idle without this which nowe the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid addeth as the life and perfection of the reſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1.</note> Euen as the Ap. S. Paule teacheth, where he asketh what the perferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Iewes was aboue the Gentiles? he aunſwereth that it was very muche, becauſe that vnto them were committed the wordes of God, the couenaunts, the law, the ſeruice of God, &amp; the promiſes, as alſo we haue in the 127. Pſalme the teſtimony of the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.</note> he ſhewed ſayth he his word vnto Iacob, his ſtatutes &amp; ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnto Iſraell: he hath not delt ſo with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nation, neither haue the heathen know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his lawes. Thus then it appeareth that not in their deliueraunce, neither in their inheritaunce, but in the word of God reueiled vnto them, their principall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and tokens of Gods fauour appeared. From Horeb and Sinai, and neither out of the riches of Egypt, nor the inheritaunce of Canaan, came their felicitie, for although that the riches of Egypt, and goods of the Caanits were greate and notable tokens of Gods fauour vnto them, yet by them they
<pb facs="tcp:20947:50"/> were not ioyned &amp; coupled with the Lord. They were not made bones of Ieſus Chriſt bones, and fleſh of his fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.30</note> as by the word and couenant and teſtimonies of God they were. For Moyſes as a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>diator betweene the Lorde and his people did in the giuing of the lawe, binde the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e two, God and his people together: putting as it were the Lords hand into the hand of all Iſraell, and giuing his likewiſe as a father into the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, making of two on: by Ieſus Chriſt the head. Therfore the Prophet Ezech.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 19.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth all other benefits that God gaue his people, to the ornaments of apparel, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to her bracelits &amp; billiments, to her rings and cheynes, and earings, to her Crowne of gold for her head, white ſilke for her body, and ſhooes of taxus for her feete, to hony, oyle, and the fineſt flower of wheate for her diet, but the giuing of his word and ſtatut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto them, to his mariage with her. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are all thoſe complaints in this Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel, and in the reſt of the Prophets con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her fornication, when ſhe left the commaundements of God, &amp; followed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtraunge gods &amp; new lawes: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo there is mention of diuorcement betwene them. This was then the greateſt and higheſt and heauenlieſt benefit that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:20947:51"/> came vnto them to be ioyned in league with God, to haue him ſweare &amp; binde him ſelf vnto them to be their God, that is their defender &amp; mainteiner, if they would be his people, he delt not ſo with any nation, or kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or city vnder the cope of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Oh Iſraell, oh houſe of Iacob, what waſt thou that the lord ſo rewarded thee, or what was Abraham thy father that he ſo viſited him? he made for him ſelfe a people onely out of Sem, &amp; caſt away Cham &amp; Iaphet, Gebal &amp; Ammon, and Amaleck he abhorred, but Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah &amp; Leui &amp; Ioſeph he loued he exalted &amp; honoured, he made them of all the world his ſonnes, and firſt begotten, all them he made Kings and Prieſtes vnto him as Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech, he made them all litle inferiors to the Angells, &amp; ioyned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſonne of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 14.30.</note> The night then that they departed out of Egypt was a day of loue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the day that Mannah firſt fel from the heauens,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 16.13.</note> was in deede a day of ioy and great gladnes vnto them: But that day that they receiued the lawes &amp; ordinaunces &amp; ſtatuts of God, although it was a cloudye &amp; a darke daye, a day of tribulation &amp; anguiſh, of feare &amp; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, of a noiſe &amp; ſound of a terrible trumpet and thunder, which all cauſed to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man heauines and ſadnes, yet in deed
<pb facs="tcp:20947:51"/> if we conſider what good that day brought to his people, what honor, what prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, what ſtate, what maieſtie, what as it were familiaritie euen with God, that clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and myſtye, that darke and dreadefull daye was the bleſſeddeſt day that euer roſe ouer them. A ſorte of poore and ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men to be ioyned in league, and as it were in mariage with God, and to haue the companye of Angells as it were bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at the mariage. My eyes are not ſo daſeled with beholding the brightnes of the Sunne, nor myne eares ſo aſtoniſhed with the thunder, not my minde ſo with ioy euer confounded, as my vnderſtanding at the conſideration of this ſo greate mercye, yea my wordes are ſwallowed in it, and my iudgement vaniſheth and melteth before it. But the Lord as Moyſes ſayth, in deede lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his people. Well we ſee then what iuſt cauſe Dauid had to remember this benefit in the Catalogue of the Lords mercies. He ſent redemption to his people, he commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his couenaunts for euer. Nowe alſo let vs a litle leaue them &amp; thinke of our ſelues and the reuelation of the worde and will of God vnto vs: that in knowing the goodnes of God towardes vs in this parte, we may labour to loue the Lorde and embrace
<pb facs="tcp:20947:52"/> his gracious calling thankfully. What the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is Englande this litle poore corner of the world to Italy and Spayne, to the great and riche countries of Aſia and Africa vnder the Turke, and other barbarous and blinde Princes, that God ſhould from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> looke as it were and caſt aſide his eye to this litle hole, paſſing ouer and contemning ſuche glorious and famous Monarchies, &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to caſt the ſeede of his word and the precious ſtone of his glory amongeſt vs, to make vs while other labour and trauell for earthly and corruptible wares, to be Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunts of this ſuch a iewell, buyers of ſuch a treaſure wherein life and ſaluation is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, and to lighten vs with the bleſſed beames of the glorious Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt. Oh before how many goodly &amp; rich nations hath he preferred vs? how hath he loued and honoured vs before other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, that in glory and riches doe farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede vs? Oh whom ſhall they ſend to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to fetch the worde of God? or whome ſhall they ſende to the deepe places of the earth or beyonde the ſeas that may bringe thence this treaſure? for the Lord hath blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them moſt iuſtly that they can not ſee the Sunne, &amp; ſtopped their eares that they may not ſmell the body of the Goſpell, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:20947:52"/> follow the Egles that flye vnto it. We were a farre of as they are, ſtraungers from God and his couenaunts with them, ſinners of the Gentiles as they, vncircumciſed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught, vnholy, nay dogges as our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth, and ſwine, and tigers: but we are illuminated, we are taught, we are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, we are made neare, euen Citizens of Ieruſalem, ſonnes of the kingdom, &amp; heires of the promiſes, and coheires with Ieſus Chriſt, who is God bleſſed for euer. Amen. Now no more vnholy, no more blinde, no more cruell, no more idle, no more abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable before God. for we are if the kingdom of God be in deede come vnto vs and into vs, that is euen into our mindes and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, then we are the lambes and doues &amp; antes of the Lorde, in all holines and paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and diligence, wayting for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt our Sauiour. For vnles we walke in theſe and ſuch like fruites of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, though the Sunne be riſen in the Realme, ſurely it hath not ſhined vppon vs, but we remayne yet in ignoraunce as we did. Yea ſurely it is an vndoubted truth that ſo much we know, as we practiſe. Otherwiſe let vs talke of the Goſpell neuer ſo much, we are ſtill deade in ſinne and ignoraunce. let vs exalt it neuer ſo high, it exalteth not
<pb facs="tcp:20947:53"/> vs, but rather thruſteth vs downe to hel, but if in deede we haue receiued the Goſpel, ſo that we both knowe the glory and mercy of God, &amp; alſo ſeeke by all our power to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie &amp; ſet forth the ſame in our life &amp; ſtudies, then are we truely lightned, and the light of God ſhall continue with vs and encreaſe in vs more and more till the day ſtarre that is the ful and perfit knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt ariſe in our hartes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12</note> when we ſhall knowe no more in part, but fully and abſolutely as we ſhall be taught, as thAp. ſayth: for ſo I thinke that ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is to be interpreted. Thus I ſay if the kingdome of God be come vnto vs in truth, and not in opinion, in harte not in face, in workes not in words, then may we both for the common benefit of the realme, and our owne grace, lift vp our hands vnto heauen and bleſſe him that liueth for euer, who hath of ſo great mercy called vs from ſo great damnation as we were in, to life &amp; glory. Oh that it would pleaſe him to make not onely an aultar in vs and in the realme for his worſhip, but fully and perfectly to build his temple in ſuch order &amp; perfectnes amongeſt vs, that we might ſee his Church begin to flouriſhe &amp; ſpread her bowes ouer the whole land: that all might haue a true knowledge of him and whome he hath ſent
<pb facs="tcp:20947:53"/> Ieſus Chriſt. For this ignoraunce that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs, and this vntowardnes that is in vs either to learne the good will of God, or to put in practiſe that which we know, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this bleſſing but halfe a bleſſing, this grace halfe a grace, this light halfe darke, nay this bleſſing no bleſſing, this grace no grace, this light no light at all. And I praye God we make: it not a curſe in thende and extreame darkenes. This in deede can not be denied but great grace is come vnto vs. But as when the arke of God was with great gladnes receiued of the Bethſanits,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.19</note> when it came from the Philiſtines, but with litle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence vſed, it cauſed a death and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of many, euen fiftye thouſand and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenty men, ſo it is to be feared and almoſt looked for, that if generally an other way be not taken in hande for the furtheraunce of the Goſpell, and perticularly euery one frame him ſelfe after an other ſorte to ſerue God, the Goſpell which ſhould be our life, will be the deſtruction and death both of vs &amp; of the realme. And as Ieſus Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the fleſh vnto the Iewes, although he was acknowledged of ſome to be the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the world, yet being generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, was enemye vnto them, and the reuenger of his contempt, So the Goſpell
<pb facs="tcp:20947:54"/> if we receiue it not in al reuerence &amp; feare, &amp; to our power labour that it may be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe receiued of all, that which otherwiſe ſhould be and would be the water of life to ſaue vs, wil be a ſea to drowne vs: the ſweete powder of our health, will be powder to our deſtruction: meate to feede vs, poyſon to kill vs: apparell to clothe and keepe vs, will with vermin infect and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot vs: laſt of all that which ſhould be a Goſpell vnto vs, wil bring the heauieſt and ſaddeſt newes that euer we heard. Well howſoeuer we vſe it, the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of it ſelfe is the precious and excellent tree of life: and happy is the garden where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is planted: yea happy be the daye and bleſſed from aboue, in which the Goſpell came vnto vs: let that moneth be reſpected of God, and let it be the head of the yeare, ioyful and pleaſaunt may it be, and let them that are ready to bleſſe, bleſſe that day: Let not darknes riſe in it, &amp; in it let no cloudes appeare, but let his ſonne be euer ſeene: for bleſſed are the feete of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that bring glad tidings of peace and life. We celebrate as it were the natiuitie of the whole world euery daye: but the natiuitie of the Goſpell we ought to celebrate euery day ſeuen times yea to make it the beginning of the ſuppu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of yeares, as we read that the Iewes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:20947:54"/> reckened their yeares from the yeare of the Iubilie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 25.</note> and from the finding of the lawe in Ioſaahs time: for then commeth the true yeare of Iubilie, the yeare of ioy &amp; freedom, and deliueraunce from bondage, when the Goſpel commeth vnto vs. We write in deed in all our letters and leaſes the yeare of the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt. But I would we ſo often conſidered the benefit and vſes of the incarnation deepely, and wayed that in our mindes. Well I neede labour no further to proue the benefit that we receiue by the Goſpell to ſet forth the excellencie &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of it: but if yet we knowe it not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently by all theſe colours, looke into the blacke countries of ignoraunce farre or neate in the olde time, or at this day voyde of the light of the word of God. Remember the blindnes of Sodome and Egypt, wherof the darkenes and night that God ſent vpon them was a viſible ſigne &amp; argument. Looke into the kingdom of Turky, if for darkenes we can perceiue it what confuſion and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is amongeſt them: looke into the Church and Sinagogue of the Papiſtes, if thorough gold and ſiluer, ſtone, and pearle, ſilke and veluet, and fine linnen, we can ſee her horrible filthines: that by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> blacke and darke colours of ignoraunce, and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemies,
<pb facs="tcp:20947:55"/> the beautifull and glorious face of the Goſpel of God may appeare. For they in deede and we (howe many ſoeuer liue in ignoraunce and idlenes euen in this place) are thoſe Cymmerians that the Sunne ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not vpon although we walke al the day in the Sunne. Nay Cymmet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are not Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metians, night no night, and darkenes no darkenes to this darkenes. The dragons and ſerpents that lye in the deepe caues &amp; cauernes of the earth, the moles that are alwayes in then holes, and batts that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the night, are paterns and portra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vnto vs of then eſtate: or rather they are already in confuſion and helliſh darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes whiche in thende they ſhall dwell in for euermore. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I beſeeche you is not he diſhonoured is not Ieſus Chriſt mocked, is not the ſpirit baniſhed? are not the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hated and perſecuted? is not the word of God deteſted of ſome, corrupt of other, and deſpiſed of all ſuch? Then there is no affinitie betweene them and God, who is light and holines: no loue betweene them, no affection, no thought of eyther toward other, but they are a farre of as the Apoſtle ſaith: they are enemies, they are two. But they who receiue the worde, are one with God, &amp; one with Ieſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea as I haue
<pb facs="tcp:20947:55"/> ſayd, bones of his bones,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.30</note> &amp; fleſh of his fleſh. Then to conclude this, we ſee what an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and highe calling it is, to haue the worde of God ſent to any people: &amp; what cauſe Dauid had to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber it, as the chiefe and principall aboue the reſt. For in deede it is the ende and ſcope to the which all the reſt are to be referred: as the place wherin he reckeneth it, well noteth it ſo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do we thinke that their deliuerance, tha then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching by the iewells of Egypt, that their inheritaunce in Canaan was beſtow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of them for their ſelues to mocke them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly fellowes, rich, braue and glorious?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.44.</note> No the Prophet Dauid and Eſay appoint the ende thereof to be farre other. For he ſayth that he made them a vine for him ſelf whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h he brought out of Egypt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.</note> &amp; I ſay in that notable ſong declareth how he planted th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m there, that he might delight him ſelfe in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of it, and as in another place he ſayth that he made a people for himſelfe. So th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n it was and nowe is muche more: euen ſo muche more, as the grace of God is more aboundaunt then it was at that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me. For the grace of God hath appeared in theſe latter daies, as th Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.</note> that bringeth ſaluation vnto all men: it hath appeared in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing vs that denying vngodlines and
<pb facs="tcp:20947:56"/> worldly luſtes, we ſhould liue ſoberly &amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly and holily in this life, wiſhing for the bleſſed hope and reuelation of the glory of the great God and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt who gaue him ſelfe for vs that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from all vnrighteouſnes, and purge vs vnto him ſelfe a peculier people, ſeruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and earneſtly following good works, and in deed moſt iuſtly:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 31.31.</note> for he ſpeaketh of thoſe dayes whereof Ieremy propheſied, that the Lord would ſtrike a new couenaunt with his people, not as he had done with then fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, from the which they ſtarted, but he would not put his lawes in then harts to do them. Then ſeeing the grace of God hath bene ſo maruelous, ſo excellent, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant in theſe dayes aboue the other, by proportion and reaſon there is greater thankfulnes required of vs to whome ſuch grace and mercy hath bene ſhewed. So that if they meete once for the praiſe of God, we ought to meete ſeuen times: if they had one preacher of it in one citie, we in one citie ſhould haue ſeuen: if they had charge that they ſhould put the commaundements and the words of God into their harts &amp; ſoules, &amp; to bind them for a ſigne vpon their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, to be a perpetuall warning in their eyes, to teach them their children, to talke of them
<pb facs="tcp:20947:56"/> walking in the way, and ſitting in the houſe, and riſing in the morning, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing downe in the night, to write them vppon the dore poſtes and corner of the houſe, we ſurely ought not to performe this alone, but euen to dreame of them in the night: Daye and night to meditate with our ſelues of them. And if their loue to this mercifull God was as the loue of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards their father, or as the loue of wife towards her husband with whome ſhe is one fleſhe, our loue my brethren ought to be as the loue of a friend who is with his friend one ſoule. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt vnſpeakeable is the grace and mercy that is reueiled by the Goſpell. The eye of none can not ſee, nor eare heare, nor hart vnderſtand it, but ſuch as haue the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God who knoweth the ſecretes of God. Now in that the Prophet Dauid ſay the <hi>he commaunded his couenant for euer:</hi> he doth not onely prayſe it for the perpetuitie and continuance of it in reſpect of God, but alſo in a word exhorteth all men to faithfull and continuall obedience in performing the conditions of their couenaunt of their part alſo. And of Gods behalfe it had bene great loue if with Abraham alone the father of the people he had ſtriken this couenaunt or with his generation after him, for ſome
<pb facs="tcp:20947:57"/> hundreth yeares: but to make it to reſt vpon the head of his ſeede ſo long after him, euen from generation to generation for euer, to graunt him this inheritance, the riches and fountaine of his mercie appeareth. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that ſome now are fallen away and their body in a maner dead, yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the truth of the couenaunt remaineth at this day. And if they had continued faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, it had neuer bene broken: for God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned ſtill ſure of the one partie for the performaunce of the old couenaunt. Then thinke a litle of this benefit, or rather let it occupy al ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whole minds in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of it that perpetually with one people (as in an arke that ſhoulde neuer be broken) the Lord laid the precious treaſure of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements. Although he departed from Siloth &amp; left alſo Sion at the laſt, yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cleane caſt away the roote &amp; branches of Iſraell, but kept and kepeth thowſands to him ſelfe, &amp; we looke for the reſt to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led euen thowſands &amp; ten thowſandes in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery tribe. This people thorow their much iniqu ty vaned and vaniſhed as the moone: &amp; oftentimes hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne &amp; nowe is in a dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous &amp; fearefull eclipſe. But by the grace and mercy of God and his word appearing neare vnto them, they haue gotten and doe
<pb facs="tcp:20947:57"/> get ſome light &amp; ſhal in thend be in the full, when God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our vnthankfulnes that be of the Gentiles, breede not great confuſion to vs which haue had them our exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple but would not learne. He raiſed amongeſt them by his worde that remayned with them, not one in one age, but many in many ages as it were Angells, euen out of their bodies: I meane, the wiſe Prophets, noble Iudges and deliuerers, holy Prieſtes and Leuits, godly Kings and Angellike Nazarits.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.28.</note> Euen of your young men I raiſed Prophets vnto you ſaith the Lorde, and of your children Doctors, I powred my ſpirit vpon your ſeruaunts, and vppon your daughters from time to time. And laſt of al as I opened my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duits in the dayes of Noah for deſtruction, ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits of grace were reueiled vnto you from heauen: yea the windowes of heauen were opened at the aſcention of Ieſus Chriſt and wiſedom &amp; vnderſtanding rained vppon all fleſh, euen to thends of the world. Thus we may remember the commendations of this couenaunt that Dauid comprehendeth in one word. And ſeing there is alſo now come to vs like grace, the ſame is alſo to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode in our ſelues. Now of the other parte in that he ſayeth, <hi>he commaunded his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt for euer,</hi> Beſide this praiſe of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb facs="tcp:20947:58"/> of God, I haue ſayd that he exhorted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vs to continual faithfulnes, in keeping the Lordes couenaunt with vs. Nowe if we agree with our ſelues one of vs with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a man with his fellowe, if we after breake our faith, we can not but condemne our ſelues of great wickednes. But if we breake with our betters as ſome Prince or King it is more both wickednes and ſhame: but if the couenant that we made with God in the beginning by our fathers &amp; haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed it in our baptiſme ſince, be by our ſinnes broken of, what miſerie and ſhame what ſinne and death hangeth ouer vs? It behoueth therefore in reſpect of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelfe, firſt that we kepe faith &amp; truth to the commaundements: and that not for an hower or the time while we heare the word, or when we come to the communion, or for a day we hang downe our heades &amp; ſome mortified &amp; conſecrat to God in ſaith and holineſſe, not only to pleaſe our ſelues if we ſee a good motion in vs though it be ſooner quenched then the lightning, but to labour to followe it, to nouriſh it, to blowe it vp, to make a fire of it, that we be not as the vnfaithfull waters which in the ſommer are dried vp, or as the dead trees which periſh in the winter, but that we remayne whole,
<pb facs="tcp:20947:58"/> and ſound, &amp; perfit as the liuing waters and Oliues of the Lorde that euer ſhed forth their ſweetenes and fatneſſe: that we make a couenaunt with God euen binding our ſelues as it were in ſtatute marchaunt for performaunce: that we make as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaketh a couenaunt of ſalt durable &amp; perpetual with the Lord to liue before him in holines and righteouſnes all the dayes of our life: that our hands and harts and knees be neuer weary of praying, our eares neuer wearie in hearing the worde of God, our mindes euer occupied in our vocation or ſomthing furthering our knowledge &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. All this we are bounde to in reſpect only of our couenaunt. Now if we thinke of him who hath ſtriken this league with vs, we can not choſe but doe it. For as Dauid ſayth here, <hi>holy and fearefull is his name.</hi> In which words two arguments are contained and forceable reaſons to draw vs and driue vs to the performaunce of it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt in that he is a holy, Secondly a fearefull God. This reaſon you know is ſet almoſt at thend of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie commaundement in Moiſes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot he concludeth them thus alway: This I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund you for I am the Lord that is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God which would not commaund, were it not both good in it ſelfe &amp; good for you:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:20947:59"/> &amp; a fearefull God which will viſit the ſinnes of the fathers vppon the children vnto the third &amp; fourth generation of them that hate me.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5.</note> Then we ſee whether to looke for helpe if we be ſlacke or weake or readie to fall in the breach of the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God. Art thou weake and ouercome almoſt with anger, with the affections of adultery in thy hart or in thine eyes? Then remember that the holy God whoſe thou art &amp; whom thou oughſt to ſerue hath forbidden them both. Art thou acquainted with ſinne, art thou an olde adulterer, an olde backebiter and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuter of hate againſt them that feare God? Knowe that the fearefull God will knocke thy pate if thou goe on ſtill in thy wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Theſe reaſons I leaue for you to thinke of, becauſe I will be ſhort and make an ende of the Pſalme, and becauſe the next and laſt verſe hangeth on this, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to declare vnto vs how to come to the ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the couenant with God. <hi>The feare of God is the beginning of wiſedom,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay: Art thou deſirous to followe the will of God and keepe his commaundementes? Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that god is an holy &amp; fearful God, with whom thou haſt a couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wherof is the keping of his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and the roote of this wiſdome is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:20947:59"/> the feare of him. This is the firſt ſtep, &amp; this is that which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt gotten, promiſe thy ſoule reſt. <hi>The feare of the Lord is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſdome,</hi> whither then ſhall he go to get this feare of the Lorde, whoſe ende is ſo pleaſant &amp; fruite ſo precious? ſhall we go to mount Sinai &amp; Horeb agayne, where we ſhall heare the thunder, and terrible voyce of a trumphet, where fire and ſmoke &amp; dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe appeareth without, and horror and feare within? Or ſhal the Lord giue into my hande a fearefull ſleepe to ſende, vpon you to prepare you to heare the worde of God? Nay theſe dayes are paſt, and God nowe ſpeaketh to vs by his beloued ſonne. Him let vs heare, let vs looke vnto him, let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the faythfull in the ſcripture &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Angels which feare him. For Ieſus Chriſt him ſelfe although the one &amp; onely ſonne, yet he feared God, as Eſay ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 11.2.</note> and was obedient to him, he feared him, &amp; was dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in prayer vnto him in the night, and exerciſed in his vocation al the day, he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God, &amp; preached the Goſpell diligently for the ſaluation of the ſoules of men, and carefully &amp; pitifully conſidering their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, deliuered them from infirmitie of their bodies. The Angels that are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen they feare god &amp; reuerence his power,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:20947:60"/> they hide their faces at his glory, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him at his feete: Ioſeph and Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ias, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell &amp; Daniell among the yong men, and Noah and Abraham, Moyſes &amp; Iob, among the fathers, Dauid &amp; Ezechias among the kings, feared him, and walked in his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundements. Theſe examples are ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs. Now Salomon he exhorteth in his Prouerbs to the feare of God, who ſeeth &amp; conſidereth al our doings, before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we &amp; al our inmoſt cogitations are naked &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no ſhadow, no cloude, no wood, no dungeon, no enchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tment, can hide vs, for he ſeeth vs that made vs: and howe can he not know vs now, that knewe vs in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, as Dauid ſaith. And thapoſtle to the Hebrews herevpon exhorteth to the reuerence and feare of God, ſeeing we call him father who iudgeth euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to iuſtice without reſpect of perſon. And to them that will occupie themſelues in the ſcriptures, many other fountaynes will appeare from which this feare of God will ſlowe. Nowe ſeeing it is the beginning or rather the principall part of wiſedome, yea euen halfe of it, we muſt caſt by what meanes ſooneſt we maye obteine it. For if we he wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers &amp; louers of wiſdome, this is the mother which muſt giue her vnto vs: if
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:20947:60"/> we be marchantes and trauellers for her, this is the key and hauen where we muſte firſt ariue: if we be Gardners, this the firſt herbe that is to be got &amp; ſet in our mindes: if we be ſchollers, this is the firſt forme: if we ſeeke for her, ſhe will bring them to her. Oh ye Tutors heare how al our labour is in vayne, if we ſeeke not to ſet this before all. We call the liberall artes and ſciences <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: but in deede prepoſterouſly. For the firſt knowledge of all knowledge, is a true &amp; grounded knowledge in the will and worde of God. And in dede if we looke for fruite at any time of good arts &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good tongues, let our firſt care be, that they feare &amp; ſerue God: that they be both brought vp in ſuche exerciſes, &amp; tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in ſuch ſtudies as encreaſe godlines: and led ſo &amp; gouerned by our example and diligence in our vocations to follow vs, as childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fathers. Theſe are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes for the ſpirite of God to be get feare of God which is the beginning of wiſedome: Nay which is the whole halfe of wiſdome, or rather as Iob ſayth, perfect wiſdome: without which al knowledge in heauen and earth is vayne &amp; fooliſh: but with which it is, I dare ſay, with Salomon the chiefeſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes. Now heare what commendation the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:20947:61"/> Prophet giueth vnto them that haue it. He ſayth, <hi>that they haue good vnderſtanding, and that their prayſe remayneth for euer,</hi> where we ſee what is thought in heauen of all ſuch as feare God, notwithſtanding they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned &amp; condemned in our Colleges, and in the world ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t a good vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding</hi> (ſayth the Prophet <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h as do ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> This commendation is drawne out of the law where Moyſes often &amp; many times vſeth the ſame verb, wherof this now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. For thus he ſayth in the 8. chapter: O that they were wiſe and vnderſtood this, that they would conſider the latter ende. And in diuers other places he vſeth this worde, when he teacheth that they ſhould do wiſely in doing the commaundementes of God. And Salomon in his Prouerbs doth often note a godly man by this title, A man of vnderſtanding. The world magnifieth &amp; lifteth vp on high, Policie, &amp; knowledge of ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng a common wealth, of conducting an army, of getting great wealth and riches by marchandiſe: But who remembreth the higheſt and moſt principall and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oueraigne wiſdome of all wiſedomes to be godlines? Theſe are ſurely things very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable and neceſſary, but if we make compariſon, theſe are not to be accompted of in reſpect
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:20947:61"/> of this wiſdome. Therefore this is called wiſdome in the ſcripture after an excellent ſorte, as though other were falſly called wiſdome, or by leaue as it were. Therefore Moyſes often times repeateth vnto them in that exhortation made to the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that this ſhall be their wiſdome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all people: that for this cauſe other natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhall acknowledge them to be a wiſe and vnderſtanding people. And in dede as God is only wiſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie, ſo this treaſure &amp; grace he giueth only to his children, when other euen his enemies excell in other giftes of the mind. Egypt hath bene famous for the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes. And Athens the ſchole of eloquence in all the world: In Lacedemon the tentes of ſouldiours and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eates of cheualtie: Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions in Italie: Lawes in Fraunce: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes in Venice: Nowe (as in old time) in Tyrus, in the lande of Hauilah are the mountaynes and vaynes of golde and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, ſcarlet, ſilke, and chriſtall in Syria, yuery and coſtly woode in Chrum, beſt wines in Damaſcus, tapeſtrie i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, and ſo foorth might ye conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der other countreys with then chiefe marchandiſe: But the feare of God, the loue of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, which is onely wiſedome,
<pb facs="tcp:20947:62"/> and onely precious, is onely founde in the Church of God. Therefore all the faithfull which feare the Lorde are all marchaunts and occupiers of wiſedome, more famous then the Marchaunts and occupiers of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus who were like the Princes of the earth, and her chapmen as the Dukes and Nobles in the world For they are al kings &amp; prieſts, as Peter and Moyſes ſaith, but our kingdom &amp; prieſthood are ſpirituall: it is not ſeene: and therefore not eſteemed. But becauſe time forceth me to breake of here, I leaue the finiſhing of theſe two laſt verſe to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tyme.</p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20947:62"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
